<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mutatus polemo. The horrible strategems of the Jesuits, lately practised in England, during the Civil-Wars, and now discovered by a reclaimed Romanist: imployed before as a workman of the mission from his Holiness. Wherein the Royalist may see himself outwitted and forlorn, while the Presbyterian is closed with, and all to draw on the holy cause. A relation so particular, and with such exquisite characters of truth stampt upon it, that each of our three grand parties may here feel how each others pulses beat. Also a discovery of a plot laid for a speedy invasion. / By A.B. novice. Published by special command.</title>
            <author>A. B., Novice.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E612_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23105</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871913</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871913</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76483)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E612[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mutatus polemo. The horrible strategems of the Jesuits, lately practised in England, during the Civil-Wars, and now discovered by a reclaimed Romanist: imployed before as a workman of the mission from his Holiness. Wherein the Royalist may see himself outwitted and forlorn, while the Presbyterian is closed with, and all to draw on the holy cause. A relation so particular, and with such exquisite characters of truth stampt upon it, that each of our three grand parties may here feel how each others pulses beat. Also a discovery of a plot laid for a speedy invasion. / By A.B. novice. Published by special command.</title>
                  <author>A. B., Novice.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1], 33-40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 2".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mutatus Polemo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Horrible Stratagems of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> lately practiſed in <hi>England,</hi> during the Civil-Wars, and now diſcovered by a <hi>Reclaimed Romaniſt:</hi> imployed before as a Workman of the Miſſion from his <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Royaliſt may ſee himſelf Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted and forlorn, while the Presbyterian is cloſed with, and all to draw on the <hi>Holy Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Relation ſo particular, and with ſuch exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Characters of Truth ſtampt upon it, that each of our three grand Parties may here feel <hi>how each others Pulſes beat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO</hi> A diſcovery of a Plot laid for a ſpeedy Invaſion.</p>
            <p>By <hi>A. B.</hi> NOVICE.</p>
            <q>In ſcelus addendum ſcelus eſt, in funera funus.</q>
            <p>Publiſhed by ſpecial Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert White.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:165723:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165723:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Right Honorable</hi> the Lord <hi>Preſident</hi> BRADSHAVV.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My</hi> LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome men meanly qualified have adventured Dedications of mean Pieces unto Princes; but my impudence, I fear, tranſcends theirs; for indeed it would better become me with a Rope about my neck to dedicate my ſelf to your Juſtice, then this piece to your Patronage: My Lord, I have deſerved death, but you know my retractations; and if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements of my former offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this State may make any expiation, I beſeech you to believe I have bin ingenuous: I preſent this to your Lordſhip, not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, but to diſabuſe the people, for
<pb facs="tcp:165723:3"/> more of theſe Conſpiracies then is revealed here is already known to you: but ſince men falling off from a party, create enmities, and dangers to themſelves, as I now expect to do, I cannot propoſe a more undanted pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to my ſelf, or deſire a more Heroical Patron to this Pamphlet then your ſelf. You my Lord, have dared in a ſtrange time to judge between a King and a Kingdom; and like a wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> you have (and yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diviſion) divided the true living childe to its own Mother. You have gone on gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly, and not like thoſe other ſcorned Judges, who now appear upon the Bench a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but durſt not ſit there when the grand Caſe was to be decided; thoſe that hated you, now fear you, and thoſe that feared you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, now begin to honor you, and believe you could not have gone on ſo, but that you are inviſibly prompted by a more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Power. You are now fixt in an Orb a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mean enmities, and we that are below, fear our enemies the leſs for your ſake. In this I flatter not, and even this blunt ſtory I hope will teſtifie me to be a man free from adulation: for here I ſpare no man, nor party
<pb facs="tcp:165723:3"/> that falls within my Verge; Here moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may ſee themſelves, how they are packt and ſhuffled for an after game, which is ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to be plaid; the Royaliſt, and the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian both may here ſee, if they pleaſe, that the Cards are to be dealt by other hands then theirs. See what complottings, what hurli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burlies, what heart-burnings here are, whilſt ſome fond men make it their main hope, and ambition to undo themſelves; becauſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, they will needs take their enemies for friends, and friends for enemies. Now the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> are landing here, the <hi>French</hi> there: now the <hi>Scots</hi> have fifty thouſand men to affront <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and yet can ſpare <hi>Maſſey</hi> ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more to take in <hi>Carliſle. Vt populi folia om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni vento, ſic populi corda hinc inde omni rumore mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventur.</hi> In the mean time, my Lord, God bleſſes your pious Cauſe, and your pious Cauſe procures you a gallant Armado at Sea, a victorious Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> another as nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous in <hi>Scotland,</hi> a powerful <hi>Militia</hi> remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning beſides in <hi>England;</hi> neither is money, nor courage, nor unanimity wanting to all theſe. Your enemies now have nothing to hope, but that confidence in your wealth and
<pb facs="tcp:165723:4"/> ſtrength will undo you: O herein let your evil counſellors be made good ones to you. But ſoft, I become a treſpaſſor upon your pretious time, and I ſhould beg pardon both for this fancy Dedication, and rude Excurſion, but that I have pardon to beg for greater offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and am not thereof as yet ſufficiently aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured. Onely if that pardon may not be granted to words, let it be obtained by the conſtant future good comportment of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My <hi>Lord,</hi>
               </salute>
               <signed>The moſt real Servant of <hi>Englands</hi> Law, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly your Honors. <hi>A. B.</hi> NOVICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165723:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou diſtruſteſt perhaps, this piece, which is now preſented to thy view, that it is a Romance, or a meer figment. But I aſſure thee tis not ſo, for ſome of our greateſt Stateſmen know the reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theſe things already: and thou ſhalt ere longe, by another more ſerious tract, which is now in fitting for the Preſs, receive a fuller confirmation. I will not call this an hiſtory, but a miſcellany rather of ſome paſſages hiſtorically written, and it chiefly contains Scotch and French Tranſactions, together with the eminent inter-actings of the Pontificall party; and ſometimes I have made mention of my ſelf, whom I hope thou ſhalt be better acquainted with hereafter. In the mean time know, that I am of a ſanguine complexion, and though I can in ſome degree pity the miſeries of the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leer, and the knavery of the Presbyter, yet I am more apt to laugh at their fooleries with <hi>Democritus,</hi> then to weep for them with <hi>Heraclitus.</hi> I have been likewiſe at <hi>Rome,</hi> but could never ſwallow down all her Fopperies; amongſt all the miracles there, I never thought any of them was a true one, but that wiſe men ſhould believe in their truth. Yet I was much bewitched with the pomp of that religion, and had died a zealous votary for it, but that God by an Incomparable <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr</hi> G. <hi>of</hi> C. C. <hi>in</hi> Oxf.</note> Divine ſent a ſpirit of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon me. And now I hope to take the Miniſtry upon
<pb facs="tcp:165723:5"/> me, and ſo draw others to God, by ſhewing them the ſtrange work of God upon my ſelf. Some will object againſt my ſtile, as was once againſt <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and ſay, that it is more vain then becomes a Divine, and more ſatyricall then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Chriſtian: but conſider the ſubject, and thou wilt ſay tis not unſuitable thereunto.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Siquis eſt qui dictum in ſe inclementius</l>
               <l>Exiſtimavit eſſe, ſic exiſtimet.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I look for no favour at any parties hands, the whole world hath no ingagement upon me, ſo highly am I inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent; yet if any moderate man ſhall be offended at my lightneſs, or tartneſs, to Him I will ſubmit, and promiſe amends in my next more ſecret, and more ſolid diſcourſe. Read therefore, and cenſure, but reſt confident, what thou readeſt here is true, and that I have written it partly to exonerate my conſcience of the guilt of an Incendiary, contracted upon my ſoul for ſome years laſt paſt, and partly to make ſome amends to my poor dilacerated Countrey. I am as fearfull of poyſoning the world with untruth as any man can be, I know well.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Qui librum pernicioſum edendum promovet,</l>
                  <l>Sibi cibum in Inferno edendum praeparat.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Let us therefore paſs on to the mater.</l>
                  <l>Haec legat &amp; triſtis Cenſor caſtuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſacerdos.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> In the laſt page of this book but one, in line 31. for <hi>Friends,</hi> read <hi>Feuds.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165723:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the indagation and redemption of Truth out of many dark counſells, black enterpriſes and fatal accidents, (that ſo through the fair perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of my experience, and knowledge, others may attain to the diſcovery of things, that now lye buried in deep vaults, below the gueſſes of ordinary men) I ſhall begin a relation about the wars ending, at leaſt when the ſame drew towards its declenſion.</p>
            <p>The late King was for his obſtinacy by ſome judged conſtant; but indeed he was one, that if he hated any man, he would never be perfectly reconciled to him, nor moved by his perſwaſions, though never ſo convincing: and yet if he loved any men (as he did ſometimes for his own ends) he was almoſt ſervile to them, and for their ſakes he would be almoſt commanded to forſake his own judgement, and knowledge. He was of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf fierce-harted, and ſubtil-headed, as his enemies felt ſoarly, when he was left to himſelf: but to his flatterers, <hi>viz.</hi> his only friends, when they pleaſed to charm him, he was weak both in reſolution, and judgement. So abſolute a Maſter he was never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs <note place="margin">Ruſtum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium legum privata prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> of diſſimulation, that doubtleſs therein he far exceeded <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and by this art he could, when he ſaw occaſion, cloſe with the moſt mortall of his enemies, and caſt off the moſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious of all his friends: and this he often did when the face of his affairs changed, and required ſuch a change in him. And though there were ſome (ſuch as his Queen, and ſome others who in his opinion could not have ſeverall intereſts from his) that did wonderfully awe him, and could drive him alwaies from his beſt reſolutions: yet there were none at all, whom he could not diſſemble withall, and reject, if he once ſuſpected
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165723:6"/> them contrarily intereſſed to his ultimate ends of Tyranny; hence it is that the world is ſo ſtrangely divided about him: ſome men that knew him only by his favours, and viewed him at a diſtance, canonize him for a Saint, and Martyr, and ſcarce allow him ſecond to Jeſus Chriſt: whilſt others who were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliged by him, and viewed him at a neerer diſtance, damn him with <hi>Judas,</hi> charge him with the blood of 500000. Chriſtians, of poyſoning his Father, of betraying thoſe of his own religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and of being guilty of perjury, and perſidie beyond all example. This <hi>Charls,</hi> when <hi>Oxford</hi> began to grow unſafe, and he ſaw he was put to his laſt refuge, knew it concerned him to perform his maſter-peece, which was in plain downright termes, to decieve his own deceiving friends, by deſerting them: and betaking himſelf to his firſt profeſſing enemies, the <hi>Scots,</hi> whom he judged of all men the moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and everlaſtingly perfidious. He fretted belike, and was ſtung to the quick, (his intelectuals being amuſed, and not ſo well able to order him) that he muſt now act a Kings part more Scenically, and not with that rigor as he was wont: but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inſtructions of his old Court moralls, he held any deluſive plot honorable that might accompliſh his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and ſo without further reluctance he thought to play the pawn of a King, ſo he might give check at laſt to the Engliſh victorious Liberty. He went not to the <hi>Scots,</hi> as imagining them more true or generous then the Engliſh: but becauſe he knew the <hi>Scots</hi> were more eaſy to be wrought upon, &amp; divided from their fellow Covenanters, then the Engliſh. Beſides, the peeviſh humour of revenge raged in him, and this was the direct road that leads to publike miſchief: otherwiſe being to make uſe of deceitfull inſtruments for deceits ſake, he would have doubted, and feared that over reaching at laſt, which he found. Tis verily thought if he had caſt himſelf upon the ingenuity of the Engliſh, and not totally loſt their hearts by thus preferring the <hi>Scots</hi> before them, he might have eaſily out-witted them, and that his own judgement had advertiſed him ſo, had not ends of further imbroyling his three Kingdomes, and effunding more humane blood overſwayed him.</p>
            <p>Howſoever, we the more active <hi>Catholicks</hi> of his party (not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165723:6"/> then privy to the ſecret negotiations betwixt him and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tril)</hi> thought his deſerved ruin was at that time inevitably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching: and being left not to the wide world, but to the narrow limits of beguirt Garriſons, we immediately conſulted what courſe was to be ſteered. <hi>Jam res ad reſtim rediit,</hi> we ſaw a ſhrewd declenſion attending us, and we ſaw as apparent a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giverſation, or neutrality amongſt our ſelves, after we had felt one an others pulſes. This was plain to us, we could no longer ſerve our <hi>Catholike</hi> ends, by ſerving a Prince ſo far tottering, and who made nothing leſs then Religion, nothing more then Tyranny his laſt object, and deſign.</p>
            <p>Now might you have ſeen whole ſwarms of us, creeping &amp; crowding into thoſe places which moſt befreinded us, either for privacy or opportunity; <hi>Oxford</hi> and moſt of the other unreduced Garriſons know this well enough.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Oxford</hi> eſpecially there was divers other Factions beſides ours; and theſe, together with the wants of the Common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who now had neither pay nor due ſupply, put all men upon new thoughts, and deliberations. <hi>Rupert</hi> had no ſmall boyes among the Generall Officers that ſided with him, and theſe ravingly curſed their fortunes, that thus had brought them to ſerve a Run-away. On the other ſide the grave privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, <hi>Ruperts Antagoniſts,</hi> though they ranted not ſo high, yet ſhewed a great repining, that his ſacred Majeſty (a pure blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy) ſhould thus leave them in the ſudds. Alſo amongſt theſe there were divers other pitifull ſubdiviſions: as amongſt the <hi>Cottingtonians</hi> and <hi>Hoptonians:</hi> The Welch were derided as lowſy Rogues, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels hooted at for perpetuall Cowards; <hi>Ruperts</hi> for Robbers; all without pay; none with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out plunder; the <hi>Hoptonians,</hi> they were the white boyes.</p>
            <p>But let us ſpeak <hi>ad rem;</hi> The <note n="k" place="margin">Sir <hi>Iohn Kempsfeild</hi> an eminent Commander of the Horſe, who never charged without a Crucifix on his breaſt.</note> 
               <hi>Kempfieldians,</hi> a faction, of which we are able, and will now give account and relation; it being almoſt the <hi>ſubjectum</hi> of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>True, we made not Sir <hi>John</hi> our Oracle, or Dictator, yet we now think it convenient to let our <hi>Catholike</hi> Party march un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his <note n="l" place="margin">Which had for his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme, the Pope and a Croſs, with words which a blind King might read with jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</note> Coroner: we are not unknowing of, nor unknown to greater Agents for his holineſs, then was he, or any that now is in the City and Army; though I confeſs his merit is not ſmall,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165723:7"/> and his reſpect greater in <hi>Rome,</hi> where I laſt left him in his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims weeds, ready to be diſpatched away for an <hi>Iriſh</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</p>
            <p>I ſhould forget the Rule of private Polity, and (I fear me) offend the authority alſo of this already formidable and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <note n="m" place="margin">Nomen R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. ſanctum habetur.</note> Republike of <note n="n" place="margin">Reſpub. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens armis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ubere gleba.</note> 
               <hi>England,</hi> ſhould I dare publikely to ſpeak all I know of the perſons of ſome men, and their now black and dangerous actings and imployments for the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of (not <hi>Charls,</hi> but)—to his ancient bloudy Tyranny: Suffice thee my Reader, thou ſhalt know all in time, it muſt firſt be my work at the Councell Table; where I ſhall (God willing) bring in a horrible large Catalogue of more perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly damnably dangerous Actors, then was in the year 1605. in that infernall Powder plot: If ever there were ſuch a fry of Devils in mens ſhapes, yea in miniſters too, crept in to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine a People and State, judge you, by that time I ſhall have diſcharged the duty of a Sound Convert, and a Native <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman, to thoſe Patriots and worthies whom God by moſt miraculous providences hath owned to be our undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly lawfull Governours: But,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Non omnes volucres Auceps, non omnia luſtra</l>
               <l>Venator ſpoliat—</l>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhall do my uttermoſt.</p>
            <p>Return we to ſee what the Catholike faction are a brewing: Each had their Conventicle; the Cavaleer Buzzard, I may ſay Bayard, had their fools <note n="o" place="margin">In <hi>Oxford,</hi> a place ſo fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, for Newes-mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> Corner, and we our <note n="p" place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally called.</note> Knaves: Some of us reſolve one thing, ſome another, all agree in this, we muſt deſert the Royall Cauſe, and (as we could) get in with the Presbyter: One (of ſuch a quality) cryes out, Ile compound and goe home, fight Dog, fight Bear; Another, I'le take the Covenant and turn Presbyter; But this laſt ſort had carryed themſelves meer <hi>Amphibiums</hi> in religion, and not openly known for reall Catholikes; but a part of us, of more hot ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, not of the laity, but of ſome ſeverall orders, did conclude it our beſt way, not only cleerly to relinquiſh our party, but to engratiate our ſelves with the Enemy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by acting ſome hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome piece of treachery, that in time we might revive the old Catholike Cauſe, by more able and apt Inſtruments then by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165723:7"/> a company of ſtaring hare-brain'd Cavaleers; who are not able to act ſo powerfully as thoſe we deſired to joyn Intereſt with, nor indeed (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks) when they had a price in their hands, were they able to get wiſdome.</p>
            <p>And for this <hi>Conjunction</hi> were there very plauſible reaſons laid down: Say ſome, Had the King prevailed againſt the People; the fawning Biſhops, to uphold their uſurped power, would have ſtampt any Religion upon their Proſelyte King, that they again might have vanted in their Lawn ſleeves and ſtoln <note n="q" place="margin">Pedo Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copali grande ineſt myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> 
               <hi>Miters;</hi> the number of us Catholikes being in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> much inconſiderable to that of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and the King not pertinacious, nor a jot ſolicitous of any Religion which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes the leaſt tittle of his monarchical prerogative: In this huddle of opinions, up ſtarts a Dominican, Fa: <hi>Car</hi> by name, now in Calice; but then known by the degree of Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter <hi>Lawrence,</hi> born at <hi>Hexam</hi> in <hi>Northumberland;</hi> (and ſeriouſly in my opinion he ſpake, (as we ſay) <hi>veteratorie,</hi> like an old Fox:) Truly (ſaid he) I can with better conſcience and more liberty fight for, and converſe with the <hi>Scot,</hi> then the Infidel; the Presbyter then the Cavaleer: I have more hopes of him for a Convert which is of ſome religion, then of him which is of none; and ſo far (quoth he) may we call the King, but his Party eſpecially, true Cavaleers: And, if we truly conſider ſome points of the Religion, and (the rigid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I may not call it, but) the zeal of the Presbyter, with its Diſcipline and Polity; you ſhall find (as in ſeverall points I could plainly hold it forth and demonſtrate the parallel) that there is no Religion in the world does ſo neerly conſent with the true Catholike faith, as does the <hi>Scotch</hi> Presbyterie; though I do not ſay it be <hi>ſuper veritate fundatum,</hi> as ours is: Beſides, ſaid he, I might urge the great hopes and probability of a Presbyters converſion; for <hi>unde aliquis flatus oſtenditur vela dat;</hi> he is ſubject to turn with every winde, no men in the world being of more unſtable mindes, and <note n="r" place="margin">Witneſs the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-pr-Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting-royall-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly-engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> giddily wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as are they: which, if <hi>Arguile</hi> in time does not, (as no doubt but he will) both the <hi>Leſlies</hi> and the generality of the Brethren will make good;</p>
            <q>Simul ac fortuna dilapſa eſt, devolant omnes:</q>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165723:8"/>
            <p> As for their guidly Covenant, it's but a <hi>Volaticum Iusjuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> ſeald with butter; which they will only make uſe of to pick a quarrell with <hi>England,</hi> when they have need of one, and are out of imployment, which the <hi>French</hi> will ſoon finde a way to put them upon, when the young <note n="ſ" place="margin">Prince <hi>Charles.</hi>
               </note> Run-away ſhall have once given an aſſurance of his real converſion to the Catholike faith; &amp; then ſhall you ſee the Presbyter the only ſtaffe we muſt lean upon: But for the Cavaleers (ſaid he) they are <hi>Duri Capitones,</hi> a company of fooliſh obſtinate Aſſes: our hardeſt taske will be to yoak theſe <note n="*" place="margin">Diſparibus bobus vix trahitur Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiculum.</note> two beaſts to draw our Pough; they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, you ſhall ſee them <hi>peſſum premi,</hi> trodden under foot by <note n="*" place="margin">Quod lupus eſt lupulum, nunquam pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt mihi viſum.</note> us and the * other.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other arguments being laid down by this Father, it was inſtantly deſired (by one known at that time generally, by no other name but Captain Saint <hi>Iohns,</hi> and yet well known ſomewhere now in this Country, of the order of <note n="t" place="margin">Sunt qui Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu nomen prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texentes homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num animas ipſi Satanae mancipant.</note> Jeſus, though he then walked the ſtreets in a Chlamys) how we ſhould ſpeedily diſpoſe of our ſelves.</p>
            <q>Non ad praeteritum conſul valet, immo futurum:</q>
            <p>The time and ſeaſon required our conſultations to be brief and pithy; and the reſult was, that ſome of the more aged, of unactive bodies for military exploits, but of buſy ſpirits to ſet things in combuſtion, and to augment feuds, ſhould be left behind, and the reſt ſhould inveigle as many as they poſſibly could of the Cavalry to fall off; which to effect, ſome of our younger <hi>Novices</hi> diſperſed themſelves to ſeverall petite Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which were not reduced to the States obedience, yea ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to almoſt all the Royall unſurrendred Garriſons in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> for really we had enough in <hi>Oxford</hi> to furniſh them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what before they were ſtored with; and there were few without <note n="u" place="margin">Jeſuits and preiſts.</note> ſome, ſome with many, I dare affirm none without any.</p>
            <p>Nor was it long 'ere the fruits of our Projects did appear, As in the great falling off of many, both Souldiers and men of eminency, which we could in any way make ſtoop to the lure of Presbyterie, and ſwallow the goodly godly Covenant: more particularly, that almoſt totall defection of the <hi>Walling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Horſe, led off by one <hi>Beard</hi> and <hi>Pawlet,</hi> in which I my ſelf had an hand:</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165723:8"/>
            <p> But I ſhall deviate too much in inſtancing on the ſeveral ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of our plots, nor muſt I be too particular, leſt the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian chance to ſee day at a little hole, and eſpy me through a cranny: My reſolution and aim is to let thee (Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) now underſtand the Cauſe of our thus, and then ſeeming compliances with that predominant Faction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for Sir <hi>Jo. Pr.</hi> which then indeed ruled the roaſt, we were better able in any notion to diſguiſe our ſelves under their diſcipline then any other; for whoſoever would (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) but down with the bleſſed Covenant, muſt be an honeſt man, let him be what he would; which we could very lawfully do, and did, being not unprovided of greater helps then Diſpenſations, ſeeing it was our onely way left to revive (as I have ſaid) the Catholique quarrel upon better termes, by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more violently rigid Inſtruments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we knew, (and I am certain it was at that time the <hi>Roman</hi> ſence) that that <hi>Polypicaput,</hi> I mean that great jolly Turn coat, the little Queens husband, being run away from himſelf and her (according to our judgment of his eaſie nature) might (for ought we know) have been ſoon brought to have ſung a <hi>Palinodie,</hi> have vailed or turned as now his ſon aſſayes and crouches (at leaſt pretends) to do; and then we durſt have warranted the caſe, that we would have reduced <hi>England</hi> into a more hideous pickle then all they had hitherto ſuſtained in their <hi>quondam</hi> broyls; for had he turned Covenanteere, which our party did aſſay by all inventible means to bring him to; and which he would have done, had not the Monarchick-Lawn ſleeves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed thoughts in him of a reſtauration to his Arbitrary power, that he muſt be <hi>aut Caeſar, aut Nullus,</hi> as of himſelf he was reſolved to be <hi>Rex aut Aſinus;</hi> or had that <hi>Spaniſh</hi> (I think I might ſay, <note n="*" place="margin">L. <hi>Say.</hi>
               </note> Sayiſh) Treatie in the <hi>Ile of Wight</hi> but taken effect; two months had never expired, before moſt of our chief ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (this Commonwealths now Governors beſt Patriots and Defendors) had all lain weltering in their own bloud: And then (as now it is) Presbyter, Cavaleer, yea, and Catholike too, having joyned intereſts, what muſt our next work have been? or what doſt thou think it now will be when it is ſo?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:165723:9"/>
            <p> Reader, Thy Genius (if thou art not made of wood) muſt neceſſarily prompt thee to the conceit of no leſs then a Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, and univerſal ruine of all the Antagoniſts and Oppoſers of thoſe Hot-ſpurs; thoſe three brethren in iniquity, who though they are ſo diametrically oppoſite to each other in principles and opinion, will out of pure malice (cauſed by their ſeveral bloody, ambitious aſpirings) joyn tails together to ſet on fire the fabrick of a moſt polite Government, and devaſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom God will not ſuffer them to tyranize over.</p>
            <p>Well, Imagine this had been done, conceit this now a doing, now done: Suppoſe we then <hi>London plundred</hi> (for what wild man thinks, or expects leſs from three ſuch mad enemies) the People and Country laid waſte, deſolate, and invaſſalled, all their enemies throats cut, our then no little Queen with her <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Jermain</hi> luſty train returned (which was granted us by Treaty) all done, all undone, and none left in the Scene but theſe three; who goes to the pot next? No queſtion, the Royaliſts and Catholiks will be ſo conſcientious, as ſtrictly to obſerve and keep each Punctilio of the pretty <hi>Scotch</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; no doubt but the Catholiques, and the Presbyters will thank the Cavaleer for his good ſervice, and reſtore his King with his Common Prayer and Biſhops, though he will be neither Papiſt nor Covenanter; if not thus, then without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, Presbyter and Cavalier muſt both turn Catholiques; and like enough ſo; I pray thee Reader, do then but conſider how ſoon we could, or can (when time ſerves) ſet the Cavaleer and Presbyter together by the ears. We are not ignorant of the old Adage, <hi>Publicae res privatis creſcunt inimicitiis;</hi> which thus we will then conſtrue, <hi>When theeves fall out, we true men come by our goods;</hi> What block-headed Presbyter or <hi>Scot</hi> (which is all one) knows not the Royaliſts to be irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable with them; whatſoever fair words, ſome old Court-Spaniel, or young declared King may give them, in hope of future opportunity for revenge, or a Crown; <hi>Priùs lupus ovem ducat uxorem</hi> Cats and Dogs will ſooner be cater-coſins then they; <hi>Lites praeterritae facilè fiunt renovatae;</hi> if not, we will put in two hundred thouſand pound to the bargain;</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:165723:9"/> Quis tam diſtantes nodus conjunget amores?</q>
            <p>Well, now they be at it, now they fight; or grant that they had done ſo; or that hereafter we ſee them too't amonſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; which ſide do you think (in plain earneſt) ſhall we Catholiques take? it is an even wager; <hi>truly</hi> neither, and yet both, if any; the weakeſt, till they have confounded each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I could give a ſhrewd hint of Orders we received in the <hi>Colcheſtrian</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Kentiſh.</note> 
               <hi>Cambo-Brittanian</hi> Expeditions; in a word, our deſign is to put them to that hard task, <hi>Penelopis telam texere,</hi> to do, and undo, till they have left nothing undone for us; But of this more in its place.</p>
            <p>I could here make an happy digreſſion, yet pertinent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and a large one if I would (but I will not) onely to ſhew the people (if they would but underſtand and hear rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) the powerful hand of <hi>All-ruling Providence,</hi> perſpicuouſly demonſtrating it ſelf in their redemption &amp; deliverance, out of the jaws, and from the Snares and Gins laid for them by theſe three Enemies; God himſelf owning <hi>This Cauſe</hi> by no leſs then miraculous ſucceſſes and unparallel'd viciſſitudes and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, and which he hath given in Commiſſion unto our moſt puiſſant and renouned Governors as his inſtruments of a moſt ſplendid Reformation, and our happily atchieved Liberty, which though it hath coſt ſo much, and the compleating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt neceſſarily require ſomething more; let us remember, that <hi>libertas potior eſt Metallis,</hi> and that we were all once but meer ſlaves, bound in our own golden chains, under an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary-ruling one man, a ſelf willed and wildly-Tyrannizing Monarch;</p>
            <q>Non bene pro fulvo libertas venditur auro.</q>
            <p>That I may recover this large deviation,</p>
            <p>I muſt now return back to <hi>Oxford,</hi> where (as I told thee) I for my part was imployed; and now behold it is ſurrendred, and I with my Comrades left to diſpoſe of our ſelves, where we had beſt hopes to create new diſtempers: Now the <hi>Oxford</hi> Articles were our onely Guardians, and (like our black Maſter) our time being ſhort we reſolve to ply our buſineſs; and truly we have not been idle, what with tawing and claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165723:10"/> the the Cavalier and Presbyter, as you will perceive ere we conclude this Relation.</p>
            <p>And (Reader, I ask you) in what mode do you think now to meete with men of my Orders? We have not onely changed the habits of our mindes but of our bodies alſo:—Our minds; for he that even now was upſie Cavaleer, high Royaliſts; he that was nothing but to make the King a Pope, that ſo the Pope might be made King, dances now after no Muſick ſo merrily as the Northern Bagpipe; the prophane Dammees left off, and nothing but the <hi>Holy Keevenaunt</hi> is heard in our mouthes.—For our bodies, <hi>Proteus</hi> is leſs then a Fiction to us; He that erewhile was a Commander in a ranting equipage, is now ſlinked into a Cobling Stall, or Weavers Loome, or Tapſters Apron, or Coach-mans Box, or Beggars Weeds, or Horſemans Frock, or Serving-mans Livery, or Taylors Shop, or a Pulpit-thumping Presbyters Iippo; into what not? It is not unknown what trade we drive beyond ſea, when no trade comes amiſs to us; I vow to God, I my ſelf have known one ſingle Student in <hi>Rome</hi> to be his crafts-maſter in four ſeveral Myſteries, and, though an <hi>Italian</hi> born, Speaking and Writing as fluent &amp; candid <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as the beſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Orator; but <hi>Hoc dubit at fortaſſe aliquis, niſi pagina praeſens idfirmâ ratione pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet;</hi> To make this good, our Governors, the States of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth (if they wil deign to hear me now their true ſervant; for they may not in this caſe, <hi>in utramvis aurem dormire)</hi> ſhall eftſoon be able to cull out many a Sheep cloathed Woof from their Stations, Stalls, Loomes, Aprons, Weedes, Livories, Shops, yea, and Buff coats; what ſay you to Pulpits too? Let not poor <hi>England</hi> (now like a Bird (Ah me) purſued by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fierce-flying Falcons, and too too neer the intended hard gripes of their cruelly-ſharp tallons) either out of a dull and drowzie ſottiſhneſs, or a phantaſtical humour of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuppoſe that I ſpeak what I know not; if I ſhould tell them I can, and (now being about to do it) will (but private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before Authority) produce a Catalogue of Catholiques, (Fathers, ſo we will be called) men of ſeveral Orders, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are Natives, who for the moſt part have changed their Habitations, gone into remote Counties, and duly go to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165723:10"/> Church too; of an incredible number now living in this Commonwealth under ſeverall Notions, which I my ſelf can <hi>Digito monſtrare,</hi> poynt at with a dry finger: I tell thee in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, There is ſcarce a Town or City but in ſome few miles of it I can furniſh thee Reader (to thy amazement be it ſpoken, and to occaſion thee to return devout thanks to God) with ſome, who have lived in <hi>England</hi> theſe 6. 10, 20. <note n="*" place="margin">Jo. B. of Ne. in Eſ.</note> 40. 50. 5. 4. 3. one and two years unknown, unſuſpected, but taken for clear contrary men: let them avoid me if they can, their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand by this time is done.</p>
            <p>Reader, think me not mad: indeed I have been, but am now come again to my ſelf: But to what (wot ye) was my minde bent in theſe Hurly-burlies? to play the Presbyter: and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther went I (trow ye) after <hi>Oxfords</hi> rendition? even to my guid <hi>Scots</hi> Brethren the Covenanters, but yet not preſently into <hi>Scotland:</hi> my colleagues and I, which were three (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed made three degrees of <note n="x" place="margin">Malus, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, peſſimus.</note> compariſon, one a <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bre,</hi> of <hi>Oxf. Sh.</hi>
               </note> Prieſt, my ſelf a Novice, the third (a <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Catesh—</hi>
               </note> prodigious name) as eminent a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> as <hi>England</hi> hath fathered theſe many years) had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined if at that time there had been <hi>Halcionian</hi> quiet times at Sea (as there were not for us guilty ſoules) to have paſſed directly over; but, diverted twixt fear of detection and zeal of working more good (upon the Presbyter) for the Catholike cauſe, we wheel'd about and got us to <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> where we found the Gentleman that ran away from <hi>Oxford</hi> playing at <note n="a" place="margin">Goffe.</note> 
               <hi>Stowball</hi> with his Sodalitia, his guid chapmen; who (as emptitious as he was) though they valued him not, becauſe <hi>ſeſe inſcendi paſſus eſt,</hi> he ſuffered himſelf to be fool ridden, yet knew well enough how to overvalue him.</p>
            <p>Here in this Gally-maufrey of people and opinions (Cavies and Presbyters) we could not in a weeks time deviſe in what ſhape to walke in: True, we had reſolved to be All-Presbyter; but the ſtate of preſent affaires ſo ordered it, that we muſt as yet be nothing but Cavaleers; for fear they (of whom there was no ſmall concourſe) as ſome of them could, might detect us what we were, maugre our ſhifting and ſniffling pretenſions to the contrary; And ſo once again we did <hi>Dextrae conjungere Dextram</hi> fall in with the Cavaleer: For ſo great a reſort was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165723:11"/> there of ſhabby raggamuffian Gentlemen, and ſome, of our old <hi>Oxford acquaintance,</hi> that we could not in civility (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne eke in policy) ſhake them off: and ſo expert are we in thoſe <hi>fraudes Daemoniacae,</hi> that (where occaſion preſented it ſelf) we became any thing to any man, (like the blacke Prince of the ayre in his witchery Apparitions, or his white Emblem the Miller, who when this winde will not ſerve him, can turn Sayls and ſerve that) and cloſed in our complyance with all, that we might but tempt ſome; which indeed was eaſily then to be done with the poor Cavies, who were <hi>Cerâ tractabiliores</hi> plyable to any advice that favoured of the leaſt revenge; but truly are <hi>Aſini Homines</hi> meer Aſſes: Here did we <hi>Cretizare cum Cretenſe</hi> hold a candle to the Divel, prompt them to what we thought would beſt ſerve our owne turnes, 'till at laſt we had fitted them to be made fooles by the <hi>Scots;</hi> (which at any time they can eaſily do, if they will but open and declare:) Thus we laught in our ſleeves (yet ſtill pretended to be equall ſufferers with them in the Cauſe Royall) which they might eaſily have perceived, had not their braines been dulled by the Devil (that <hi>egregius deluſionum artifex)</hi> and totally intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the ſpirits of <hi>Mandragora:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor had we ſtaid long here, 'ere great numbers of the Royall Party came flocking to the <hi>Scotch</hi> Army, in hopes of more worke for the <hi>Chirurgian:</hi> which truly had then been done, as well as ſince, and now again (if they dare) <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ab Aquilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ante No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, quam vulpes venari gallinas ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſedeat:</hi> the South wind will blow from the North before theſe Beggars will leave troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us.</note> like to be, (for <hi>jam tertia vertitur aeſtas)</hi> had they not feared their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cocke King might (in a new-periwig plot) have put upon them the old <hi>Oxford</hi> trick; or had not that currant ſum of <hi>Bona &amp; legalis moneta Angliae</hi> been too praevalent an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with them to abandon and deſert him, whom they valued not really at the eſtimation of 200000. <hi>Scotch</hi> bawdles; To be ſure, our endeavours were not wanting to exaſperate all Partyes by all the ſtratagems our wits could deviſe; ſeriouſly, our fomenting had even then made the Tynder take fire, though we could not do it till here of late; Now tis done; judge you how near it was then brought to an head, (but what will not money do with a <hi>Scot,</hi> (now their Cataſta is in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;) what will not a <hi>Scot</hi> do for money? An ingenious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165723:11"/> Monſieur (at this inſtant, I beleeve, in <hi>Scotland)</hi> at a frollick meeting, in <hi>France,</hi> of ſome freinds, amongſt whom I jovially paſſed for currant, ſaid thus, (cunningly;) I'le undertake for halfe a Kings price their whole Nation will D—themſelves, and the ſtricteſt Formaliſts among the guide Breethren account it no ſinfull Engagement to eat nothing but ungodly Pearke for an whole year; The plot (I ſay) by our nimble-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand inviſible fomentings then grew near to an head; Near indeed; Not only excepted Delinquents unpardonable Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leers, but Catholikes, yea known Prieſts and Jeſuites, we alſo by a generall order were publikely quartered in the moſt afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and ſecure Townes and Villages: You will think it ſtrange to hear me ſay there was at that time (and how much more now they have, like Sampſons foxes, joyned tayles) to the number of two Regiments of Catholikes; nay (to my certain knowledge) there was one meer-all-wholly-a Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment new raiſed (before the money came down from Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) and reduced, under the conduct of my Lord <hi>Synclare</hi> a Presbyterian-Papiſt; and this alſo I proteſt to God I can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme for reall truth, there was not only then to be a conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>Montroſs,</hi> but <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels to be tranſported, and a war with <hi>England</hi> then reſolved upon; (ſee what money can do) had not theſe policies over ballanc't their reſolutions;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the world would have cryed ſhame upon them, that they ſhould ſo ſoon have broken their own Covenant with the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> which they reſolved to referre to a longer time, hoping to inſinuate to the world, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> firſt began with them, whenſoever they ſhall have a minde to invade, ordiſturbe our tranquillity;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That they ſhould more then hazzard the loſſe of the great ſum, if they did too ſoon ſhew their teeth; and not being able to pretend the leaſt reaſon that would hold water, why they ſhould pick a quarrell with their even now Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates: And as cunningly alſo did they repell the inceſſant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of their priſoner-King; telling him, their ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of him would prove for the beſt, and that it ſhould be to no other intent but to furniſh them with more plauſible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for a war and breath with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> States: For
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165723:12"/> indeed they well conſidered, that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> could do no leſs in juſtice <hi>upon that Capitall Delinquent,</hi> then what might bear them out in the opinion of ſeduced Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as a ſufficient excuſe for their many peremptory, bawling, miſcheivous papers and meſſages, which (ſince that) they have interruptingly dared to trouble our State with, beſides that their other years Run-away <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and yet ſtill are they ſo impiouſly politick (or rather blockiſhly impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent) as to make this their pretence, that what they do, is for their guid King (&amp; his ſon) whom, rather then they would have been at the charge to have kept him till this time, I dare ſay they would have poyſoned (in which that travelling Nation is very <note n="b" place="margin">Witneſſe their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen Dr. Crichton his Sermon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yong Stuart at the <hi>Hauge.</hi>
               </note> expert) or have put to a more exemplary death then that <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad generum Cerer is ſine caede &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine pauci Deſcendunt Reges &amp; ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cd morte Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranni: Iuve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> Few Tyrants in their beds do dye, But head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long they to Hell do hye.</note> condigne and yet honourableone, which he here received by the Plebiſcitum:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sponte ſua cecidit, ſub leges arcta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> jura;</l>
               <l>Sed rigidum jus eſt, &amp; inevitable mortis:</l>
            </q>
            <p>But all this while the poor Cavaleer is hood winkt, and held in ſtrong ſuſpence; neither can they imagine whether theſe Scotiſticall <hi>Pioneers</hi> will be <hi>Scots</hi> or no <hi>Scots,</hi> (but <hi>Scots</hi> will be <hi>Scots:)</hi> And they allowed them too bread and cheeſe pay, from the Engliſh; which indeed was no ſmall boon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the ſmall Nook ſo vaſt an Army (which had been at <hi>Hereford)</hi> were glad to be thronged into: poor Animals, theſe credulous Cattell, or blind Bears, as they were then, ſo are they ſtill led on by the noſe (in hopes) by their worſt firſt Enemies; what elſe makes them <hi>Ampullas &amp; ſeſquepedalia ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba—</hi>bolt out ſuch high bug-bear Raunts? what elſe makes them triumphingly ſo heave up their heavy heads, and be ſo ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to bragg (meerly on the dependance o'theſe crafty Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamountaines) that,</p>
            <q>Grata ſuperveniet quae non ſperabitur hora,</q>
            <p>That ſpeedily a day will come which will pay for all: Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſt, let me tell thee in love, <hi>Sapientia prima eſt, ſtultitiâ caru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe,</hi> Do not be ſo unwiſe as to be ſo fooliſh as to beleeve a <hi>Scot:</hi> But I do <hi>ſaxum Syſiphon urgere,</hi> beat the ayre to <note n="*" place="margin">Vecordes verbis non ſubiguntur.</note> no purpoſe: Ye Ardelio's think ye out-wit all the world beſides, when <hi>(faciunt nae intelligendo ut nihil intelligant)</hi> theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (in plain <hi>Engliſh)</hi> would ſeem to know all things, and yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165723:12"/> they knew nothing, but are a company of dull eaſily beguiled Aſſes.</p>
            <p>Yet wellfare my Lord <hi>Synclare</hi> (if there be any <hi>Scot</hi> worth the whiſtling after, I am confident it is he) I cannot be oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of his affable deportment, and tender ſympathy he had of the conditions of ſome of the pittiful Renegado gentlemen. I dare aver, I can reckon up betwixt fourty and fifty hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore high-flying Dammee-Raunters, now in a lowzie ſtarving condition which he releived, and were admitted ſometimes to be drunk with his gor-bellied brother <hi>Harry,</hi> that old Court-Curr, <hi>Harbert Price,</hi> That <hi>Welſh-French</hi> Gallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poaſted fellow <hi>Turburvil Morgan,</hi> That eaſie Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, <hi>Durham</hi> gent. Colonel <hi>Jack Forcer,</hi> with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which I could name, of greater quality, who did eat of his free-quarter bread, or had periſhed: But O the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of ſome Gentlemen of lower quality then theſe! <hi>Synclare</hi> ſometimes for the great ones would go a begging to the great begger for a ſute; but for theſe poor ſouls not a doit but <hi>Scotch</hi> fragments: If ever any of thoſe Gentlemen, which were then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, confide in a <hi>Scot</hi> again, I ſhall ſwear they are Cur-Spaniels, and horribly bewitched: Amongſt theſe latter lower ſort did we three get in for quarters; pretending as much indigency as the meaneſt of them, and ſearching out who were Catholiques amongſt them, that ſo we might Liſt them under a certain Collection; which very ſecretly and cloſely we had got raiſed of the <hi>Northumberland</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Gentlemen: Nor did we eaſily give credence to any that urged himſelf a Catholique; for indeed that would have made our number ſwell too great (the Cavies being at that time ready to turn any thing, except Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, for ſome money to be chirpingly drunk, and ſing away ſorrow;) but many reall ones indeed were found, a great company of them being crowded into a very good quarter, at Miſtreſs <hi>Thyrwalls</hi> houſe, a Catholique widdow, in a mile of <hi>Hexam</hi> in <hi>Northumberland;</hi> amongſt whom was Sir <hi>Thomas Tildeſly</hi> with a tottered tail as well as the reſt, who ſent for Mr. <hi>Bre—</hi>to ſpeak with him, whither we being come, with him found a company of lamentable Tag-rags (outvying our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165723:13"/> diſguiſe) going under the names of Colonels, Majors, and Captains; ſome playing at Iriſh, ſome at Gleek, all at Noddy, except Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> who with a poor Scholar was playing at Cheſs; Mr <hi>Bre—</hi>asking his buſineſs with him; He told us, that he had been informed of our Negotiation, and deſired us to enter his Liſt in ours; amongſt whom we found ſome doubtful and unknown names; which, we told him were not ſafe to be admitted for fear of diſcovery; He aſſured us, they were all very faithful Royaliſts <hi>(which did not pleaſe us)</hi> and wanting very much, even ready to periſh with hunger and nakedneſs; amongſt which that Scholar, for whom Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> ſeemed to be very highly ſolicitous: No ſooner almoſt was he with ſome of the reſt admitted, and had once or twice received collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but ſome of them cried Roaſt-meat to their unadmitted Comrades, which truly fell out very inauſpiciouſly for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, worſe for the Cavies; the collection ſtopt, and we reſolved for a diſperſing march: For, neer about this time was the bargain made, and hands ſtruck betwixt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Scots,</hi> for that Old-New-Nothing; and with him all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> both Catholique and Cavies to be ſurrendered priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners upon the ſumm (as juſtly we might) for Incendiaries. This news being ſoon ſent us (and in troth not too early, for it was in the nick-time) from <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> by ſome of our Agents there, we well hoped to have had ſome laughing ſport; for after our flight (which was into <hi>Scotland)</hi> had they ſtayed a little-little longer, the poor Cabbs had been all ſurpriſed, if not ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to our Parliament Army then upon a cloſe march; but in <hi>Edenbourgh,</hi> we had not been an whole week, before the ragged Regiment came tottering in there, many thouſand millions ſtrong, thicker then when they firſt ſhifted into the cleanly <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army, out of Gods bleſſing, yet not into the warm Sun, but a ſtinking cold climate</p>
            <p>And what can you devize theſe poor gentlemen can do here for ſubſiſtence? truly it was miraculous to ſee the miſeries they endured at the hands, and in the ſight of thoſe unpittying hard-hearted Cannibals the <hi>Scots:</hi> nay, they did not onely commiſerate but baſely <note n="a" place="margin">Deſolatos deridere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia eſt.</note> deride and <note n="b" place="margin">Nil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet infoelix paupertas durius in ſe, Quàm quòd ridiculos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines facit.</note> jear at their calamities, ſaying, there gangs a brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cavaleer, whylk fought and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165723:13"/> run away for his King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now I believe thou ſuppoſeſt the Catholique alſo to be hard put to it here, or that (at leaſt) he was forced to live on the main ſtock; no (really,) we found friends enough here, even of our own Order. I can aſſure thee (Reader) a Catholique delights in no air (beſides his own) ſo well as in a Presbyterian. Moreover, we here met with Monſieur <hi>Montril</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Agent, who was then conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the <hi>Scotch</hi> States, about the laſt <hi>Hambletonian</hi> engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though ſince they account it ſinful for being baſted; with him we immediately fell into ſome conſultation and action, as you ſhall hear anon.</p>
            <p>But O the poor Cab, his guts pay for it; there was not one of them but hunger had taught ſome occupation or other to get money, and it were but enough to buy <hi>Scotch</hi> bread: ſome Captains got their meat by dreſſing Troupers horſes, not one <hi>Scot</hi> breathing would beſtow a Bawdle on an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> without ſome ſervice done for it; they would rather call them <hi>Lownes,</hi> and bid them get out of the Countrey. The Scholar (I ſpake of) he drives a trade with the Colledge, when inſtead of ſome ſubtil queſtions, the Maſter put him (as he told me) to expound a Chapter in the Bible, which he did till he had pounded out four or five <note n="a" place="margin">A poor ſumm in <hi>Scotch</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</note> pund of them, and more had he had of them, but that they demanding his name, and he telling them, they ſaid it was a Popiſh name, (as I remember it was <hi>Pawlet,</hi> or ſome ſuch name) the Scholar wittily replied, we have many good Proteſtants of that name in <hi>Herefordſhire:</hi> after this great purchaſe he and one Major <hi>Thomas Right</hi> ſet up a trade of making ſweet powder for hair with Rice, a trick of the Scholars, by which they lived well, and cozened the <hi>Scots</hi> very handſomly.</p>
            <p>But no going back was there for them, whither they could fly God knows, themſelves know not. Reader, thou muſt not conceive, that of all theſe Gentlemen there were none which were thus diſtreſſed, but meerly for their fooliſhly and falſely conceited loialty, though the moſt part were ſo indeed; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly there were many, <hi>Homines gregorii</hi> amongſt them, raskally fellows, ſome Theeves, ſome Bankrupts, ſome abject Sons, ſome Prodigals; as the Scholar would often make me
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165723:14"/> take pitty on him, when he would uſe to tell me, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Miſerabilis fuit homun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio:</hi> He was a caſtaway.</note> that an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Father, and hard Mother in Law was his Parliament; many (like him) had ſeveral occaſions that reduced them to theſe dilemma's of miſery.</p>
            <p>And now was there a convention of the <hi>Scots</hi> States in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, which puts the Cabs (as poor as they were) into a ſhrewd fright, and themſelves into a puzzle, which way they ſhould diſpoſe of them; for had they rudely betraied them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, which demanded them in the bargain upon the ſumm, they had too ſoon diſplayed to the world their perfidious dealing with the Cabs Idoll; but, which is the main thing they had then falſified with the <hi>French</hi> to whom they had ingaged to ſell theſe cattle for ſo much the head, to ſerve in their wars againſt the <hi>Spaniard</hi> till ſuch time as they had both ripened their quarrel againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and then ſhall the poor Cabs be brought back again, to uſher on, and ſet a face upon the Popiſh <hi>French,</hi> and Presbyterian <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Deſign, which what it is, you will here towards the end.</p>
            <p>The general bruit now blown over all <hi>Edenburgh</hi> was, that the great blades were to be culled out and ſent to <hi>London;</hi> but for the reſt, if they would take conditions, they ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed from the hands of their enemies, and be accommodated to ſerve ſome forraign Prince (the laſt is true enough, but the other as falſe as a <hi>Scot)</hi> their ſtinking States onely made an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this purpoſe, that thereby they might give an <hi>Item</hi> to excepted perſons to ſecure themſelves; and (as they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs) to my knowledge they had private orders given them, to clap themſelves into a diſguize, and not to walk ſo publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſtreets; and thus they ſhew themſelves <hi>Scots</hi> ſtill with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> States, for by thus doing they conceived they ſhould be able to evade, if not flatly deny any juſt demands agreed upon in the former paction between <hi>England</hi> and them.</p>
            <p>Theſe raskally doings being thus carried on for ſome weeks in Hugger mugger, and the Cavaleers having ſome ſlender allowance, they knew not from whom; at laſt they all began to inſinuate to them, that the <hi>Scots</hi> had picked a juſt quarrel with the Roundheads, and that they ſhould in a ſhort time invade,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165723:14"/> upon pretence of redeeming the even now ſold Bondſlave from his captivity, and bring him (like a painted Pageant) in pomp up to <hi>London:</hi> But this poor pretence, though politike enough to catch the credulity of the throughout gulld Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leer, becauſe opinionating ends ever by words; yet we (who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver judged of mens words by their ends) knew the inſide of the piece to be clean contrary; for, the <hi>Scots</hi> (though they had an egging minde to have more plunder) were adviſedly too cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly to be thus valiantly fooliſh, knowing the ſtrength and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of that gallant dreadfull Army of <hi>England,</hi> whom they durſt as well eat Peark as look upon; though they now make ſome flouriſhes, of purpoſe to get ſome <hi>gelt</hi> for the Son as well as the Father; and then you ſhould ſee them fling him off, and creep to an Engliſhmans elbowe for another confederacy.</p>
            <p>In the mean time while things fell out very happily for our Party, the Cabs knew nothing but what we thought fit to tell them; and they very quietly acquieſced in our Oracles: For now was I (with my two forementioned Comerades) imployed afreſh by Monſieur <hi>Montril,</hi> about ſuch a like bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs as we had in <hi>Northumberland;</hi> which was to muſter all the Gentlemen we could ferret out, and to take a ſtrict and particular liſt of all that were Catholikes; which we in time effected, and delivered it to the Monſieur, who commanded us to attend him the next day at <hi>Hally-Rood houſe,</hi> where D. <hi>Hambleton played Rex,</hi> and kept court as Lord <hi>Protector</hi> and Steward in the Dotage of his Cozin: whither when we came, and were called for to the Preſence, The <note n="e" place="margin">We all conferred in the french tongue.</note> Duke (a right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary, pure Saint of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as being pretty competently po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, abundantly zealous, and very indifferently religious) firſt demanded of the <hi>Agent,</hi> whether we were ſuch as he might dare to confide and imploy in his Maſters buſineſs, we being Engliſhmen, and for ought I know (quoth he) Cavaleers: they are ſuch (replyed the Monſieur) who do <hi>omnes unum ſtudere,</hi> and whoſe Characters I have received from no ſlender Teſtimony; beſides, this gentleman (pointing to Mr. <hi>Catesb—)</hi> being my old acquaintance, and a reall ſervant to the <hi>Flur de luis;</hi> whom (being Engliſh; and, as they are) I dare ſooner truſt then any men alive, none being able to do
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165723:15"/> our buſineſs with that influence and facility they may, with their old dear acquainted Oxonions: <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> (quoth the Duke then to us) were it not prejudiciall to your ſelves, as you have no reaſon to think, I could wiſh that I knew how to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall my reſpects to your ſeverall qualities: But be confident, I am overjoyed in this bleſſed opportunity of ſerving his <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty:</hi> Here are up and down this City a crew of odd fellows, old beaten Souldiers of the King of <hi>Englands</hi> party, who can now ſerve for nothing better then to fill ditches, thereby to ſalve their loſt honours, when they ſhall ſhed their bloud in the ſervice of a more puiſſant Prince, to whoſe gracious Majeſty I ſhall ever devote my beſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance: Let it be your part (therefore) as much as in you lies, to prepare them for this Expedition, which you will the eaſlyer effect, by taking theſe few verball Inſtructions with you: <hi>[much to this purpoſe]</hi> Firſt let them underſtand by you from mee, the great compaſſion I take on their ſeverall diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſad conditions, and how ſtudious I am to better it, and to render them capeable of doing his <note n="f" place="margin">A double-tongued <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </note> Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> more good ſervice, and that to this end I am very willing to engage my ſelf unto hs Majeſty of France's <hi>Agent</hi> (here) for ſome competent ſum of money for their ſubſiſtance and future pay, which who ſo <hi>liſts</hi> may receive; and that I will freely (but privately) procure of the States of this Kingdome Paſſes for their going beyond Sea, and will alſo provide veſſels, and be my ſelf at the charge of their Tranſportation: all which I ſhall do as a demonſtration and pledge of that ſervice I owe to my yong Mr. the Prince of <hi>England;</hi> whom <hi>(be ſure to tell them what I ſay)</hi> by their and others recourſe to him, with ſome foraign Princes aſſiſtances, I hope (and little doubt) ſpeedily to ſee in an invaſive capacity to revenge his <note n="g" place="margin">Si non ante diem Parcae ſua fila ſecan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> Fathers indignities, and powre out flouds of the blood of thoſe rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Roundheads: You ſhall alſo (ſaid he) take money with you to give advance to all thoſe who ſhall enroll themſelves as ſouldiers for the French expedition, (for under that Notion you muſt tell them it muſt be carried on) that ſo the States of this Kingdome may not be unfurniſht of a pretence and excuſe againſt the urgings of thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> when they ſhall ſee us
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165723:15"/> play foul play under-board: But above all, I beſeech you, that you make a diligent enquiry into the temper and imployment of ſome of thoſe <hi>Anglers;</hi> I am told there are ſome amongſt them of moſt accompliſht parts; and my Agents in London have given me warning, that there are certainly ſome of them imployed by the Engliſh Parliament as Spies and Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers concerning the tranſactions and conſultations of me and this State; <hi>Let ſuch be nippily markt and taken notice of; and where you ſhall find deſerts in any other of them, as conducible to our purpoſe, proceed to collate large and particular encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> Gentlemen (quoth he) you may not; and I know you are not ignorant of the end of our deſign; in which, while we ſeem to help theſe baſe ſcoundrels, our ambition is to ſerve his <note n="h" place="margin">King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, according to our long-continued and lately renewed obligation, againſt either Spaniſh or Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh adverſary; at the preſent to fight the one, and ere long to invade the other; the latter of which his Majeſty may hereafter eaſily atchieve, having ſo many plauſible pretenſions on his ſide; as not only the reſtauration of his neareſt Ally, but (which is the main ſtring of his bow) his entring with ſo many native Engliſhmen, which will ſtop the people from banding againſt his forces when they enter, and occaſion many thouſands to joyn with them againſt their own Natives and Countrymen; which when God ſhall pleaſe to bring to paſs, I ſhall then be openly able to declare to the world, how much I am in Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance his ſubject, and in conſcience your ſervant.</p>
            <p>Thus after our moſt humble regratulations to his Grace for theſe <hi>pictae tectoria linguae,</hi> and indeed his affable and noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment to us, with his tender reſpect of our religious quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (for the Agent had whiſperingly told him what Mr. <hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               </hi>was) we were now departing the preſence, when preſently we were remaunded by the Monſieur, who told us, that he had a very great deſire to ſee as many of the gentlemen as could be got together at a Rendezvous, if the Duke held it ſafe; to which Mr. <hi>Br</hi> anſwered it were more convenient to defer that for one week longer, till more of them had liſted themſelves, and by their Advance recruited their tottered condition, and amended their equipage; to which the Monſieur anſwered,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165723:16"/> Gods death, let it be even ſo, or elſe they'le take me for a very merry gentleman; meaning belike, He ſhould be unable to hold his countenance, and reſtrain laughter.</p>
            <p>And now the poor Cabs do <hi>captare Ranam</hi> ſhoot at a crow and kill an owle; they have brought their hogs to a fair mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, (like the Devil when he threw them into the Sea,) of a foul event, they have a fair labour, they muſt not only be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be beaten out of the Kingdom, but be <note n="*" place="margin">Ni reſipiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant fuſtibus &amp; flagris nae ipſi vapula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt.</note> beaten in again, to uſher in and make room for thoſe, who when they have ſerved their turn of them, will uſe them and their King both alike; nay they ſhall be forced to fight againſt themſelves; <hi>Sic vos non vobis, &amp;c.</hi> ſo that the more victories they win, the more miſerable they make themſelves, and un-king their Prince: This plot was never ſo ſtrong againſt them, as tis at this moment, as in time I ſhall declare: But they will not be induced to beleeve the French to be other then reall Aſſiſters, and that they do not catch at their crown; and, I muſt confeſs, their reaſon ſeems to be ſomewhat ſolid in this particular; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſay they) we know our King to be reconciled to the Roman-Catholike Church, and hereby he hath ingratiated himſelf with, and engaged all the Catholike Princes of Europe for his aſſiſtance: <hi>Ah Freind,</hi> I know the pulſe of the French not to beat ſo violently for Religion, when a crown lies at ſtake; they hope (Ile warrant thee) to ſee a <hi>Lewis</hi> crowned in Londre, as there was a <hi>Henry</hi> in <hi>Paris:</hi> But they ſay, His Holineſs hath obliged all Catholike Princes to be aiding, and amongſt them the French; who, if ever he wins <hi>England,</hi> (tis more then probable) maugre the Pope, will count himſelf fitter to be <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> then he that juſt now was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to it to regain a crown: And this is but meerly <hi>bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum ratio,</hi> all the reaſon they have.</p>
            <p>Well, but let us look back and ſee what we Presbyterian-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valeers are doing at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> amongſt the Cavaleer-Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians; Our time is wholly ſpent in liſting who liſt to taſte of the <hi>Eſca</hi> of our hooks; and no little trouble was it for us to ferret them out of the ſeverall holes they had buried themſelves in; Our firſt two daies work was, to pretend the diſcloſing of a great ſecret to all we met, that they ſhould give notice to all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165723:16"/> the right Cavaleers they knew, to meet at a Green a quarter of a mile beyond the Kings Hally-Rood-Houſe, neer a little Alehouſe there, called the <hi>Worlds end,</hi> where Duke <hi>Hambleton</hi> had by us intended (out of his pure pitty) a diſtribution of money to all diſtreſſed <hi>Engliſh</hi> Officers, and Gentlemen ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Kings party, according to their ſeveral qualities, and that there would be made ſome propoſitions for the ſeting a foot again of our old quarrel with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rebels: O how greedily was this Gudgeon ſwallowed! Thoſe that had but twelve <note n="i" place="margin">One penny.</note> black dogs, drunk a health that night in <hi>Scotch</hi> Ale to the brave Duke; and thus we made every one prove a Decoy to his Comrade; and our appointed time being come, our work we found done to our hands, and ſome Punds drunk upon ſcore in the Dukes health before ere we came at them, where we found the ſilly ſouls extreamly frolick and blythe, <hi>Hic ſaltat laetus, hic eſt ſermone facetus,</hi> every man fancying va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to himſelf (and building caſtles in the Air, as yet ſtill they do upon a <hi>Scotch</hi> foundation) according to the defect of his judgement and diſcretion;</p>
            <q>Ex improviſo fallitur omnis homo:</q>
            <p>And ſo they are reſolved to be once more <note n="*" place="margin">Imbelli ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniculo ne ſuſtenteris.</note> deceived by them before they will learn better forecaſt.</p>
            <p>Nor when we came did we piddle with them a whit, but forthwith accoſted them with the moſt preſtigious ſugar can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did words we could invent, not forgetting one tittle of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, which we confirmed for truths, by a certain token the Duke had ſent by us, which was twenty ſhillings <hi>ſterlin</hi> to drink his dear Maſter the Kings Health, and a confuſion and damnation to the Parliament, beſides, half ſo much for the King of <hi>France</hi> his Health; deſiring them to accept of theſe poor favours he had ſent them, as a token of what more he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to do, as a ſympathy of their loyall ſufferings, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as a demonſtration of his fidelity (though formerly miſtruſted) to his Maſter: Thus having told our tales, and recruted every man with a conſiderable ſumm in his pocket, (beſides their heads full of <hi>Nobilis Alla)</hi> we deſired them all quietly to diſperſe themſelves, and in the mean while to put themſelves into as hanſom an equipage as they could, till our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165723:17"/> meeting again (that day ſevenight) in the ſame place, when if we did not preſently fall upon action; we told them, we were commanded to aſſure them upon the Dukes honor, they were ſafe, and that there ſhould be a very competent and large allowance offorded the very meaneſt of them all; and ſo they ſtraglingly parted like fools as they came;</p>
            <q>Qui leviter credit, deceptus ſaepè recedit:</q>
            <p>I cannot call it good nature in them, but a ſhallowneſs of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, contracted through cuſtomary overmuch talk, more boaſting, through too little obſervation, and no pondering; for certainly no cattle in world are more eaſily beguiled then the Cavaleers generally by an over-weening credulity; the true occaſionall uſe of a <hi>wiſe diſtruſt</hi> and <hi>ſlow Belief,</hi> either not reaching, or elſe miſplacing, ſeldom deliberating, till ſurround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with fears, who are ill Counſellors, and never determining but upon hopes and wiſhes, who are falſe Aſtrologers: The dull <hi>Phrygian</hi> could <hi>Serò ſapere,</hi> the Cavaleer will <hi>nunquam;</hi> He is alwayes extravagantly talking of many generations paſt; never once roundly conſidering, how that <hi>Then</hi> was <hi>Then,</hi> and <hi>Now</hi> is <hi>Now.</hi> But, to our Relation:</p>
            <p>We ſtaid not this night, till we had informed the Agent how far and fair a progreſs we had made in the buſineſs, who ſeemed very pleaſant at the relation of the ſeveral pretty paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages at our <hi>Tap-laſh Rendezvous,</hi> ſome Devotions being that night performed at his lodgings (at which the Duke was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and many other <hi>Scotch</hi> Gentry, though ſome people will hardly think it) we had the honor to be commanded to take our repaſt there that night, and waiting his Honors leaſure, and further pleaſure with us, he told us, there was no more to be ſaid, till the Duke had compleated many things with the States, which to him he had, ingaged for: I will onely add this (ſaid he) for our comfort. I doubt not (by the fair progreſs we have already tranſacted with theſe <note n="k" place="margin">The <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </note> people) but to ſee our three <note n="l" place="margin">Cabs, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants.</note> enemies beaten by themſelves, and a way made for the banner of Chriſt, and the Standard of my Maſter, to be in time ſet up in that baſe adjacent Heretical plot of earth: Maſter <hi>Ca—</hi>told him, though our hopes were once great by our influence on the King and his party, yet it would be greater then ever, if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165723:17"/> we could once ſee a conjunction betwixt the Royaliſt &amp; Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and both willing to accept of aide, from his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty: you ſhall ſee ſtrange things done (quoth the Agent) if ever we can but bring them to ſhake hands, though with the teeth outward; which in ſome time (though perchance alſo with ſome little difficulty) we ſhall bring about: The Royalliſt is ſufficiently madded already; for they ſay, they will take the <hi>Turks,</hi> yea, the <hi>Devils</hi> ſide to conquer <hi>England,</hi> and in time you ſhall ſee, we ſhall work on the diſſatisfactions of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, that we ſhall bring them to joyn with us and their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to overthrow their brethren and friends.</p>
            <p>And now (Reader) I can buſie thy fancy with little of this weeks work, onely the great mirth of the Jovialiſts, they are no ſmall boys now, and (Ile warrant you) drink no ſmall Bear: New faces ſtill appear to be liſted, an't were for the <hi>Turk,</hi> all is one; thirty <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhillings advance was then a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ſumm; In three or four dayes the Agent ſent a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to command our attendance at the Dukes Court, when he (we no ſooner being come) asked us, whether our number did increaſe, or decreaſe? We aſſured him, that we had liſted thirty ſix more then we had advance money for, which was preſently delivered us; But ſaid he to the Duke, how ſhall we provide now to keep them together from running away? By doing as you do now, (quoth the Duke) meaning by letting them have money enough belike; but it was preſently reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon, that a party of Horſe ſhould ſcour the Country <hi>England</hi> ward; and it was given out, that it was onely to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and take up wandring <hi>Engliſh</hi> Malignants and Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and to ſend them to the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> But the next thing put to the Queſtion by my ſelf, was, who were fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to be choſen for the Officers of theſe liſted men? Well ſaid, (quoth the Agent) a thing indeed moſt neceſſary next to be conſulted on; for either we muſt pitch upon ſome of our own friends, or at leaſt their enemies; my meaning is, Catholique or Presbyter, the laſt being as ſerviceable to promote our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes as the firſt: Here is a noble Gentleman (quoth Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Cat—)</hi> one Collonel <hi>Forcer,</hi> who is not onely diſcreet, but really their enemy (and your ſervant) yet very popular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165723:18"/> them (for the fools have a vein ſtill to love us, how plain ſoever our practiſes appear againſt them,) he is one that by a certain intereſt (beſides Religion) would be glad by any means to advantage and ſet forward the <hi>French</hi> Deſign; being alſo not ignorant of the greateſt ſtate of affairs, and doth very well know how great hopes we have for the advancement of the Catholique Cauſe, by bringing the Cavaleer under the Lee of the Presbyter; Introth you have onely anticipated me (quoth the Monſieur) tell him I kiſs his hand, and deſire a word with him, for had you not mentioned him, I muſt have had ſome conference with him about ſome higher concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And thus again we parted with Orders to return with moſt convenient ſpeed, which the next day we did, the Colonel in our Company; and after ſome private conference betwixt Monſieur <hi>Montril</hi> and himſelf, we were ſoon diſpatched, and gave out among the Totterdemallions, that all things were now concluded, but that a Colonel General was wanting, which we doubted would be a <hi>Scot,</hi> if we did not ſolicite the Agent, that we might ſelect Officers among our ſelves; and amongſt us none ſo fit and faithful a Conducter as would noble Colonel <hi>Forcer</hi> be, which they every one preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
            <p>Well, now approaches the ſecond and laſt day of our liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh <hi>Worlds-End Rendezvouz;</hi> where (after high <hi>Bravadoes,</hi> how we would plunder <hi>London,</hi> and torture the Roundheads at our return into <hi>England,</hi> making no diſtinction between In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent or Presbyter, when we had ſubdued them both) it was at laſt generally given to underſtand, Thar the fartheſt way about was our neareſt way home, and that we muſt firſt viſit <hi>France,</hi> where we ſhould lye at Rack and Manger (Free quarter) in Garriſon againſt the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> till ſuch time as a League and <hi>Amneſtie</hi> could be procured betwixt the <hi>French</hi> and them, and untill the difference betwixt the Independent and Presbyter did flame to the very height; which we aſſured them would erelong ſo come to paſs, and that it would prove a very feaſible buſineſs by flattering the one, to deſtroy both.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:165723:18"/>
            <p> But behold, the grand <hi>Pa—</hi>the Monſieur approaches, where (by reaſon of different languages) at the firſt accoſt there was nothing but dumb ſhews, and <hi>Serviteur tres humbles;</hi> but there came a <hi>Scotch</hi> Interpreter with him, who was commanded to expreſs the Agent in this wiſe: <hi>Gallant Sirs,</hi> his Honor (here) hath commanded me to let you know, that though he be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a <hi>French</hi> man, yet he was ever naturally devoted to the ſervice of great <hi>Brittains</hi> Monarch, and that by the ſolicitation of the moſt renownedly vertuous <hi>Henrietta Maria,</hi> their Queen his Miſtreſs, he was now imployed by his Majeſty of <hi>France</hi> to agitate concerning the <hi>Engliſh</hi> affairs, and in ſpecial particular for the reſtauration of his moſt diſtreſſed Majeſty of <hi>England;</hi> and underſtanding, that ſo conſiderable a number of his party (moſt gallant Genlemen and Commanders) had by the cruelty of the enemy been beaten into this Kingdom for refuge and ſafegard, things indeed fell out more ſucceſsfully for his buſineſs then he could have wiſhed for, or expected; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe now he was not onely in a capacity to ſerve their Prince, but the Gentlemen in their miſerable exigencies; and to put them into that way which muſt of neceſſity be followed for the reducing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rebels: He hopes he hath no cauſe to doubt of the averſneſs of any in the promotion of this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if there be any ſuch (for perchance you may not be alike zealous in a good cauſe) it is deſired, that they would pleaſe to urge their reaſons, to ſhew, why it may not be accounted more ſafe to go into <hi>France</hi> to your Prince, then to return back into the jaws of your mercileſs enemies: Your accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation there ſhall befit Gentlemen of your quality, and in prcoeſs of time you ſhall finde your work done to your hands, by ſome unknown ſervants of yours, who are now ſtirring up of fewdes, and flinging Marrow-bones betwixt thoſe two Curs, the Presbyterian and Independent; yea, ſome there are, that are inviſibly acting in their very Councels and Army; whom if they cannot involve into a quarrel one againſt the other, they ſhall raiſe up ſome ſtrange <note n="*" place="margin">The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, a Plot of the Jeſuits.</note> ſpirits amongſt them that ſhall vigorouſly oppoſe, and perchance utterly confound them both; If this ſtring fails, there is another ſtronger for the Bow. And now <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> if there be any of you that make
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165723:19"/> exceptions, or deſire to have any one of the Articles more plainly expounded to you, (for there were articles drawn and agreed upon betwixt them) let them now be pleaſed to ſpeak; there is nothing in which his Honour is not very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to give each of you ſatisfaction to the full: and whoſoever of you have any requeſt to promote concerning himſelf or friend, he may be heard, and in reaſon his requeſt granted: <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> Your Quarters are now taken up in Leith, where you may freely reſide by the connivance of theſe States, that when time ſhall ſerve you may be there ready to imbarque.</p>
            <p>So they all with great unanimity declared their forwardneſs in the action; his Honor then ſaluting them with a generall <hi>Sa Sa</hi> parted from them, telling them he hoped ſhortly to be with them, and to ſee them all ſafely arrived in <hi>France,</hi> and in a little while in <hi>England</hi> again.</p>
            <p>And now for the <hi>Antycerae,</hi> for here are fools enough to make a pretty formidable Fleet: In ſhort time a right merry Gale commands our perſonall appearance a boord, whither we ganged as drunkenly reeling as the Ship, <hi>omnium getherum,</hi> all together; <hi>Quot capita, tot ſenſus,</hi> as many heads, ſo many windmills and aiery Caſtles; Seventeen daies (which is much for ſo ſhort a journey) we were tumbled at Sea, enduring two very ſhrewd tempeſts; and really the Caſt-awaies were like to be wrack't; yet all this did hardly allay the furious impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the <hi>Damme Blades</hi> till the Seamen bid them for ſhame prepare for death; which ſome of them did only by banning and curſing the Roundheaded <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Rogues; yet at laſt we (by a ſtrange preſervation) were whirled into <hi>Dunkirke</hi> Harbour, where the then naturalized Governour for the French, (Raunt zau) maugre the Agents Letters, ſent us packing again, and would not ſo much as admit us to put our noſes within his theiviſh Garriſon, when he underſtood but what countrymen we were, (ſo ſtrong a jealouſy have the French ever had of the Engliſh) fearing that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> having almoſt brought their buſineſs at home to an handſome period, might alſo have imployed us in a ſurprizall of that Port of Robbers; thereby to have opened a gap to the liberty of the miſerably perſecuted Reformiſts there; a Work worthy
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165723:19"/> our States, when God ſhall pleaſe to put them upon it, which in bleſſed time may be done, when the Caviſh <hi>Remora's</hi> of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall once have their bellies-full of rebelling and jarres.</p>
            <p>Well, again we hoyſt Sayle, and in ſome 10 or 12. houres put in at Saint <hi>Johnſtones,</hi> betwixt Bulloine and Calais, the very place where <hi>Harry</hi> the Eight won Bullione; And here we got ſome provant for our weather beaten paunches: the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants gazeing upon us, and admiring what minde had blown thither ſuch a company of odd blaſted fellowes: Here we look't for an Army to be gone into <hi>England</hi> out of hand; we had thoſe amongſt us that askt of the French where the great body lay, that were bound for <hi>England;</hi> They ſwore by no ſmall bones, that they more doubted of Engliſh to invade there; the name of <hi>Cromwell</hi> being more terrible amongſt them then ever <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight was: this made the Gallants loll their ears and laugh at one an other: Not long after we had Quarters aſſigned at Gain in <hi>Picardy,</hi> though we were not like to gain much by the bargain; For that accommodation (which the Agent ſpake of in <hi>Scotland)</hi> befitting gentlemen of our quality, we found to be the lowſie ſtraw which the <hi>Suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> had left behind them and a cruſt when we could catch it; So that we were like to be fed with a bit and a knock; for in a monthes ſpace we were drawn into the field, up to <hi>Durlane,</hi> for the releif of <hi>Armantiers,</hi> not one Monſieur-Article obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but all diſhonorably broken: In a word, to be breif, within a quarter of a year that brave Gallant number of <hi>Fuſees</hi> were ſquandred all to peices, knockt o' the head, or ſtarved: Oh the horrid miſeries, incivilities, affronts, hardſhips and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt theſe poor Caitiffes felt and received at the hands of the French, by many degrees (if poſſible) ſurpaſſing thoſe former miſeries they endured by the Scots! There was not a man amongſt them, that if he were found <hi>napping,</hi> (as we call it, <hi>lagging)</hi> but the French uſually butchered him for no other reſpect but <hi>quatenus</hi> Engliſhmen, ſuch is their love to the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all party of <hi>England:</hi> I have now concluded this part of our Comi-Tragaedy, leaving the poor Cabs in the ditches, and thoſe of them left alive to unſpeakable miſery, the judgements of God purſuing them, whither ſo ever they fly, for theis hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165723:20"/> impieties of debauched Drunkeneſs and helliſh Healths to mens Damnations; for their familiar Oathes and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, their wild whorings, their cunning adulteratings (and then awingly-borrowings, but abſolutely robbings of) the Families, where ever (under feigned freindſhip) they (for their ſecret ends and way of ſubſiſtance) by their joviall inſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations creep into; and eſpecially for their fooliſhly-diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and blindly-obſtinate treacheries againſt their deareſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent their Country, in an humorous defence of a Tyrannicall King and Papiſticall Queen (<note n="a" place="margin">King Iames Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the L. <hi>Darley</hi> hangd it <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Queen of Scots his Popiſh Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his ſecond ſon both behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> King Iames him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his eldeſt Son more then ſuſpected to be both poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; His Daughters husband with her ſelf and children driven out of all; His Favorite (and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths Traytor) ſtabd: Her father an Apoſtate and ſtabd; her Mother a Popiſh Incendiary, the place noted unfortunate afterwards, where ever ſhe came: Pr. <hi>Ch.</hi> reſolved to turn Turk, but he will be revenged on the Engliſh; the Duke of <hi>Yo</hi> to be a Cardinal; <hi>Rupert</hi> as good as the beſt in the bunch &amp;c.</note> two ſtrange families, to them and theirs moſt fatall) the unlucky offſprings of a Learned <hi>Scot,</hi> and a Warlike Apoſtate by the Fathers ſide, and of a Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <note n="b" place="margin">Such a hunting King and dancing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Queen In the Engliſh court were never ſeen.</note> Wanton, and a Florentine Popiſh W. by the mothers: And now I come to relate ſome obſervations and certain paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, which befell and intervende during my ſtay in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ca.</hi> I know not upon what ſuddain change of minde, or whether (moſt ſecretly) imployd in ſome Agitation, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly got away for Saint <hi>Omers,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Spain;</hi> whence he promiſed after ſome ſeaſon to return and meet us at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh court at <hi>German en Lay;</hi> Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> and I ſpeedily ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roatcht thither, where when we came, we found a very ſtrong report flying up and down amongſt the Religious, (and yet choakt with as much privacy as could poſſibly be) that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be done for <hi>England</hi> this year; yet in ſhort ſpace it was blown over: For it was given to underſtand, that the Presbyter had not wholly fallen off and deſerted the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which was meant by that laſt but new Southern <note n="c" place="margin">Colch. <hi>Ken.</hi> and <hi>Wal.</hi>
               </note> rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which the French and catholikes in generall were on edge to have a finger: But, upon better deliberation, (having not then the power and influence on the Scots and Engliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Presbyters, which by reaſon of the yong King they now have<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) they have reſerved their ſtrength for <hi>this very years</hi> after game: And moſt ſtrangely confident were they all, that a breach one
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165723:20"/> way or other would be wrought betwixt them; eſpecially when they heard of the Peoples eager violence crying out for Juſtice againſt the <hi>Capitall Delinquent;</hi> for they hoped this would have reduc'd the Parliament to an hard <hi>Dilemma;</hi> as whither it were fitter, to deny the requeſts and clamours of the generality of the people, and ſo incenſe them; or elſe, by ſtopping the due courſe of Juſtice, to claw with a few inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate diſcontented <hi>Laodiceans</hi> whoſe luke-warm neutrality (having in time of yore, put their hands to the plough of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) turns them cleer off from what they had firſt inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves to compleat: Which peice of Juſtice as it muſt of neceſſiry have been done, they reſolved would (without doubt) very ſufficiently provoke the Presbyter; (happily becauſe they had not the honor of doing it themſelves) the Cavaleers themſelves are generally (all of them) fully of this opinion; and, ſay they, had theſe been ſuffered to domineer over us, we had not found that equall intermixture of juſtice with mercy, which we now do find at the hands of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent; the little finger of their gouty-loyned Covenant, which none of us would take, would have proved heavier to us then that line of an Engagement which we all have taken; nay they now ſay, that a reconciliation betwixt them is meerly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; and yet they all hope, if they ſtir no more in rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ſhall ſee the happy day of a generall pardon from their now Governours.</p>
            <p>But that which was the greateſt obſtruction, and did moſt of all binde the hands of the French from medling in the laſt new Presbyterian and Malignant Rebellion, was firſt not only the Spaniſh difference (which cauſed them to have an eye in their pole) not being yet made up, as anon I ſhall ſpeak of; ſecondly, nor only the proneneſs of their own enſlaved people to attain that precious liberty which the Engliſh had chalkt them out the way of; but thirdly, (and which is all in all) Cardinall <hi>Mazarin,</hi> Father <hi>D</hi> and <note n="a" place="margin">a <hi>Ies.</hi>
               </note> Le M. had not yet done their do with their yong <note n="b" place="margin">P. <hi>Ch.</hi>
               </note> Pupill; but a fair and hopefull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs they had made in the buſineſs; They had brought him (by that time we came thither) to this, that he would very uſually (but cloſely) go to ſee the faſhion of a <hi>Private Maſs</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:165723:21"/> with his Mother; and to my knowledge I have ſeen, that he can croſs himſelf prettily of a young Beginner; but to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> indeed they could not of a long time bring him, (though he might not be aſhamed to confeſs what in forty weekes was ſo viſibly ſeen by that young <hi>French</hi> Lady of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor; another young dainty <hi>French<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Engliſh</hi> Heir Apparent) yet at laſt great promiſes prevailed, and the better to confirm them, his brother <hi>Jemmy</hi> (whipt into a Religion by his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and turning like a twyne threed) was forthwith to be <hi>Capt</hi> a Cardinall, and (beſides) all Catholique Princes ſhould be invited and conſulted with for an unanimous invaſion of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But loe news comes a loft upon the wings of the Winde, that the people and State of <hi>England</hi> had ſummoned his Father to an high Court of Judicature to bring him to a trial for all the innocent blood he had ſpilt, and the hideous devaſtations he had cauſed: This was no little good news to the Cardinalical party, (I mean the Jeſuitical) for in my next I ſhall ſatisfie thee concerning their cunning workings; how even theſe, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo much charity and friendſhip to the Son, did ſeek by all machinations to expidite and accelerate this high piece of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon the Father: and now ſay his Tutors to him, If they proceed to death with your father, it will prove rhe better for you; for it will utterly allienate the hearts and affections of the people from them, and you ſhall finde them to be the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly violent for your re-inveſtment, not conſidering the change of your Religion, which by any means ſhall not be publikely known to any but your good Catholique Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> till ſuch time as you have wreſted power enough into your own hands to protect it and your ſelf in it; but indeed the Lad had ſome of the Fathers aſtutiouſneſs in him, &amp; preſently asked the Cardinal the ſame queſtion w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> his Father once did the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> when he was almoſt eaſily intreated to have turned to the Faith Catholique; How ſhal I (ſaid he) ever expect to be King of <hi>England,</hi> if once the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould underſtand I am turned Catholique? To which they eaſily gave a ſatisfactory reſolution, telling him, That (as the caſe now ſtood) he muſt never look to be admitted but by Fire and Sword; the main force of arms
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:165723:21"/> muſt make way for him, neither could he ever in the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability atchieve that, or put it in execution, without the aide of Catholique Princes, which they will never be brought to act in, without a firm aſſurance of your reall and faithful converſion.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, I muſt ingenuouſly acknowledge, for ſome term of time he made a little pauze upon this hard Lecture; but no ſooner was there certain news arrived of his Fathers decollati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but he was heard by ſome of his attendance to ſwear a great oath, <hi>That he would turn</hi> Turk, <hi>or any thing, to be revenged of the bloody</hi> Engliſh; which mad boyiſh words were like to loſe him the Lord <hi>Hopton,</hi> and other of the moſt conſiderable of his party of the Epiſcopal Proteſtants; for they plainly ſaw the great endeavours therewere for his converſion; beſides, that moſt times they were ſecluded and barred from their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendances; and indeed they could not otherwiſe judge, but that he would eaſily be induced to <hi>Popery,</hi> who was reſolved to turn <hi>Alcoranite,</hi> or <hi>any thing</hi> for revenge: Beſides, all his Chaplains were turned to the wilde world a grazing, except onely thoſe who did conſtantly aſſert their real converſion, as that <hi>Scotch</hi> diſſembling Hypocrite (yet moſt rare Linguiſt) Doctor <hi>Chrichton</hi> did, and ſome few others: <hi>Hopton</hi> 'tis true (and ſome more which I could eaſily name) was packing up to be gone, and deſert ſuch a dangerous cauſe and raſh Maſter (had he been admitted to pardon;) but he was woon and wound back again by that old ſubtile Fox (that Church-Papiſt, or rather Atheiſt) <hi>Cottington,</hi> and by the great Proteſtations and intreaties of many others <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> (not for the leaſt affection they bear him, but) well conſidering, how fit and plauſibly he may ſerve to uſher in a forraign Enemy, and be a <hi>Noſe of Wax</hi> to the <hi>great deſign of</hi> Englands <hi>ſecond Conqueſt;</hi> eſpecially being ſo popular amongſt many of the Weſtern ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced people, who think verily that good man will never come with thoſe who have a deſign clearly to conquer this Nation, and fall to their old <hi>Fire and Faggot</hi> burning ſport.</p>
            <p>And now the great Overtures for a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Treaty are ſet on foot, a difficult thing to be brought to paſs, yet harder to be concluded, (ſuch a natural Antipathy is there betwixt theſe <note n="*" place="margin">Spa. &amp; Fra.</note> two Nations:) but the Jeſuites (I know not how) at laſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165723:22"/> effected it in ſome ſort, and there was canvaſing the buſineſs in private betwixt them above a quarter of a year, before the world could as much as take notice of ſuch a thing; and when it did break forth, (ſuch things cannot be hid in a dark Lanthorn) Propoſitions on both ſides were ſo ſmothered, (at leaſt adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated, before they came to the ears of men) that ſcarce any Neighbour Nations could give their poſitive judgements what would be the concluſion and reſult of that <hi>Game-underboard:</hi> The reaſon of all this covert cloſeneſs was, becauſe their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was moſt concerning that pretty prey of <note n="*" place="margin">A hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome plot of ground ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conveni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and after which the Popes chops have a long time water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting by the Jeſuitical Plough of <hi>Italian</hi> Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (guided by Belzebub, and drawn by a mixt Team of <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, to which <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington is</hi> Carter) to convert that good Paſture of Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtants into <hi>Romiſh-</hi>Arable, that it may be ſharply reaped by the Sword, and the grain cruelly threſhed out (at the Barn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>door of <hi>Rome)</hi> by the Scepter of a Catholique Conqueror: it were excellent for the Pope, then he might here again glean <hi>Peter-pence,</hi> convert eaſie ſouls, and carry more ſtraw to <hi>Rome;</hi> who ever remained firm (reſolved) to be left as ſtubble for the fire.</note> 
               <hi>England:</hi> It was urged by one to the other, that never was there a fairer opportunity then now to be revenged of thoſe reforming A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates, to fall on and ſurprize them, they thought it fit to make Hay while the Sun ſhined; and the moſt they yet diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree about, is who ſhall have the crop when it is mowed: The <hi>French</hi> make mountainous offers of returning ſuch and ſuch <note n="a" place="margin">Fl. Cat. &amp;c.</note> places into the <hi>Spaniards</hi> poſſeſſion, if he may be ſuffered to enjoy the conqueſt, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> being to furniſh him with ſo much money, men, arms, ſhipping, ammunition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſo long a time: Alas noble Monſieur, this is not like to fadge, for it runs diametrically oppoſite to that general opinion of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> of an univerſal Monarchy; Truly Gentlemen, I humbly conceive, You reckon before your Hoſt; You count your Chickens when the eggs are adled: We have an Army (and, becauſe our confidence is not in the fleſhly arm of man) that by the power of God will not fear to meet you half ways any where, at any time; and we have not a people ſo witched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſotted, that becauſe you bring along with you one whom you make your ſtalking horſe to your miſchievous deſigns, will therefore open the door to let him in, that ſo you may come crowding in at his back; Do your worſt, we fear you not, though there were eighty eight Nations more of you, all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading us on the next fifth of <hi>November.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:165723:22"/>
            <p> But here a great while they have ſtuck faſt in this Quagmire, not for a long time reſolving one way or other, leaving the deſperate <hi>Engliſh</hi> Youth in ſad dumps to think, and a great greedy ſuſpence to imagine why they ſo long procraſtinate their aſſiſtances: And here (really) a man would have thought they would have been plunge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> everlaſting; but what they have done in it, (their Tutor) the Devil knows; only thus much I am ſure of, they have made the Lad believe, that without fail this Summer (and very probable) they will fall on, and put him (out of doubt) out of his pain: To this purpoſe he is put upon a work to beguil himſelf, I am mightily deceived if he do not find himſelf Cony-catch'd in it, and all the <hi>Lutheran</hi> and <hi>Calviniſt</hi> States and Princes beſides, (who will find themſelves meerly drawn in) that have engaged in ſome aide of men and money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They ſhall onely lead the Van, and be the forlorn Hope to the Rear-Catholiques, who will come powdering in too, but in their breeches with a vengeance; Well, but to theſe the young Papiſt hath ſent Beggars to implore aide for the Proteſtant Cauſe in good <hi>Tru-ly;</hi> having Commiſſioned his Emiſſaries to engage, and make promiſe of a very faithful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paiment of all their ſeveral charges and expences, by a general Tax upon the people, when (the skyes falling) he ſhall be able to catch Larks in <hi>England;</hi> which to conſtult, about they are to meet at <hi>Breda,</hi> where now a Babel of them are concurringly tumbled together; The Catholike he ſtands behinde the Hangings, and neatly obſerves all their reſolutions; nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed doth any thing paſs as reſolved without the Councel-Boord of <hi>France,</hi> their Approbation and Concurrence, a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of their Tranſactions having been weekly poſted up to the <hi>Lowre</hi> and St. <hi>Jermans,</hi> and eſpecially whereſoever the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reſidence of the <note n="*" place="margin">Mazarini.</note> Cardinal be at any time fixed, he having the onely influence (by order from his Holineſs) on all the Acts there paſſed.</p>
            <p>So that now (Reader) I will give thee a touch and but a glympſe of the invading plot, how it is laid; becauſe I intend (aſſoon as I have received my packet, and conferred circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; for indeed I am now out of <note n="a" place="margin">Suſpected a Convert.</note> their books) to come again ſpeedily into the Preſs, and ſpeak plain Engliſh; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165723:23"/> thee ſome ſcore of <note n="*" place="margin">Catholikes, Prieſts, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, and trayterous Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</note> Names, which will even aſtoniſh thee to think, that we have ſo long hugged ſuch vipers in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes: And then will I ſhew thee the ſecond part of this ſtory, beginning from <hi>German en Lay-to Breda,</hi> and ſo forward, in which there ſhall appear plain truths, and thou wilt be forc'd to believe them in ſpight of thy malignant heart; when it ſhall be made evident to thee, that at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they take it for granted, that we are already conquered, and reduced to the Faith, ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent are they in the Reſolutions of their main Ayders, the Presbyterians: <hi>Exitus acta probat,</hi> The proof of the pudding is in the eating good Mr. Pope.</p>
            <p>[Ambition to rule, is more potent in One that is up; then Malice, to revenge, prevalent in one that is down:</p>
            <p>And,</p>
            <p>To one that is down, Auxiliaries obtained, not by coin, but upon courteſie (wherein may be craft) are moſt dangerous:</p>
            <p>For,</p>
            <p>A Forreign Prince needs no greater invitation to ſeize upon a Crown to himſelf, then when requeſted to regain it for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</p>
            <p>Yet,</p>
            <p>Let no Civil Diſcords encourage any Forraigner to invade, ſince they that are factious among themſelves (and jealous one of another) for this or that party, are ever (eſpecially being already provided with an old conquering Army) more ſtrongly prepared, when the whole is at ſtake, to encounter with a common Enemy; for, whom Civil Commotions ſet at variance, Forraign Hoſtility reconciles:</p>
            <p>And ſurely,</p>
            <p>A wiſe Forraigner would be cautious in undertaking an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſive Deſign upon the report of ſuch as are exiled their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:165723:23"/> Country, whoſe ends expect Advantages from their Aſſiſtance, their miſeries laying hold of all Opportunities, and ſeeking to be made whole, though upon their ruine; for, an Invader repelled, muſt expect (at the next bout) to be Invaded;</p>
            <p>However,</p>
            <p>If Forraigners will be Fooles, who can help it? Reader, be thou wiſe, in relying on God, and being true to thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: Let no flattering wiſh deceive thee, malice urge thee, price nor promiſe bribe thee, nor ought elſe tempt thee to take part with any Enemy of the State: Aſſure thy ſelf (if thou doſt) whoever wins, thou art loſt; If the State prevaile, thou art branded for a Rebell, and markt for death; If the Enemy proſper, thou ſhalt be reckoned as a Traytor, and not ſecured of thy life. He ſerves the State, that deſtroys a Rebell; And it is a common thing for a forraign Prince, that loves the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to hate the Traitor: Above all, preſume not on Secreſie, ſuch confidence hath undone many: Innumerous are the waies of finding out a man, beſides finding him in the very act; Nor think a good wit can aſſuredly carry thee through an ill buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Every man may not be the Wit he thinks himſelf; And if he be, or more, yet none ſo cunning to cover, but to diſcover there are others as wiſe. If you think well to ſeem faithfull, you muſt needs think it is better to be ſo. <hi>Humanum eſt errare, condonare Divinum:</hi> Whoever wanders (as I have) let him quickly return to God, his Country, and himſelf. The Shorteſt errours are the beſt: Be not aſhamed to be wiſe, be thou encouraged; for <hi>Peter</hi> (through the mercifull aſpect of Jeſus) doubled the grace by repenting, which he had loſt by offending:]</p>
            <p>Now for the Plot, it is thus laid: (Reader, thou haſt it from a good hand, and an affectionate heart, to thy good; Believe it to thy preſervation, for which be thankfull; and doubt it not, in ſimple ingratitude to God, and to thy deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:) The Scots, that is, the Presbyterians both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> (for London hath a luſty finger in the <hi>Breda-pye)</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:165723:24"/> are the fore horſes to draw on the good Catholike Deſign; The little Queen (this every one knows) hath laid a ſtrict command on her Lad, by all poſſible means to compoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and cloſe intereſts with his guide friends the <hi>Scots</hi> &amp; <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Presbyters, upon any kinde of conditions, how baſe or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble ſoever, ſo that they may be brought to grapple with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> State; Theſe are to advance and keep ſome ſpudder in the North, to draw down a conſiderable party thitherward; the Engliſh-brethren are by all poſſible means to work ſome ſtrong diverſion (if they can, or dare) in the Southern, or ſome other parts: The <hi>Montroſſians</hi> at firſt were deſigned to keep warm the backs of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and preſently with their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Mercenaries, <hi>Danes, Swedes, Suitzers, Kerns, Normans,</hi> and ſome <hi>Germans,</hi> to advance as neer the guide town of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> as they could: But this (too late for their advantage) was perceived; and did put the Leſlyans to more then an halt in their reſolutions, even to a turning faces upon the <hi>Hurrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Invaders; ſo that now it ſeems they are remaunded, and have croſs orders to hoyſe for <hi>Ireland</hi> (as tis given out) to make all cleer there in a trice: but this is but a flim-flam, they are (as I have ſome reaſon to ſuppoſe and report) to joyn with the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> in the Weſtern Iſlands, who is only uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and imployed for nought elſe, but to cover an Out-landiſh Invaſive Enemy, with his plauſible preſence, and ſome Engliſh with him: and others to prick on the Jockies to be ſent in their ſteed into <hi>Scotland,</hi> but not till the Engliſh and Scots come to Handy-gripes. Nor are any to ſecond <hi>Hopton</hi> but theſe, and ſome Flemiſh aide by ſea and land, till he hath made the Gap wide, and the way cleer for ſome other Party: and then, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from all parts and Kingdoms ſome ſweeping Armies of Catholikes to land in ſeverall places at once, which (as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valcers themſelves do brag and give out) ſhall come like a floud, and in a trice ruſh and overflow the whole land like an <note n="*" place="margin">Et tunc im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſo impetu Hoſtis confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ingruit.</note> Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: But of this more in my next Treatiſe, which I am confident will be convincing enough to ſtir up the ſpirits of the moſt venemouſly unſatisfied ones that are, to an unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous oppoſition of (at leaſt) all the forreign Enemies of our Peace and Country: who if ever (as God forbid) they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165723:24"/> ſhould come to gain a conqueſt over poor <hi>England,</hi> be ye aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, Presbyterians and Cavaleers too, that ye alſo muſt to pot, and are in as great a Predicament (of confuſion) as he that is now and ever,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The moſt faithful Servant of the Common wealth of <hi>England;</hi> And real Convert to the Reformed Religion; working by Jeſus Chriſt in the power of the <note n="*" place="margin">Sedulò In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirationibus internis at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo.</note> Spirit.</signed> 
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Commune diſcrimen Diſſidentes conjungit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:165723:25"/>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:165723:25"/>
            <head>Epilogue to the Author.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOur Papers you were pleas'd to communicate to me, I here return; and as you deſir'd, they have been read over, and I am ready to give you this account of them. Firſt, I beleeve you report nothing but truth in them: for theſe particulars agree ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly with my generall <hi>Obſervations.</hi> 2ly, I beleeve many of thoſe, who have been formerly of an other opinion, will be convinced with your report. 3ly, I beleeve you will hereby gain no diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, nor incur danger except onely from thoſe, who are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and knowing that you ſpeak truth herein. I mean plainly if you provoke any enemies hereby, it will be the Cavaleers, the Papiſts, and Presbyterians, and yet all Papiſts, Presbyterians and Cavaleers, though they know theſe things are more then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, do not certainly know, by any privity of their own, that they were ſo acted as to particulars, as is here deſcribed: and therefore you need not fear all. As for the Independents they are rather juſtified, then provoked hereby; and as for the Levellers, though you pritty well deſcribe them, yet you inſiſt not much upon them; and if you had; they are not very formidable at this time, partly becauſe the major part of them never yet fell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally from the Ordinances of God, or from us, and all ſuch now as fell not ſo far have quitted their blaſphemous, Atheiſticall ringleaders, and I am in great hopes, that ſome of them which have not yet retracted, may be woone upon by your cleer, inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous diſcoveries, therefore do not withdraw one foot back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; <hi>Tutum eſt cumtimeas inferre gradum.</hi> You know what <hi>Scipio</hi> ſaid being once imploy'd upon an hard ſervice: <hi>Neceſſe eſt ut eam, non ut vivam:</hi> and you know better what our Saviour ſaid; <hi>He tbat will ſave his life ſhall looſe it; and he that will looſe his life for my ſake, ſhall ſave it.</hi> You ſeem to me to be inſpir'd as <hi>Sampſon</hi> was againſt the Philiſtines, ſpare not then to provoke them, ſend your fire-brands by the tayls of your coupled foxes into their ſtanding corn: if you ſurvive your conflict, you will injoy your victory here: if not, yet you will pull down the pillars of your enemies, and periſhing together with them, you will be inwrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with a more glorious lawrell hereafter. You need doubt none, but the one-eyd, mungrell, half-witted medly of Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leers,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165723:26"/> and Presbyterians; and yet theſe, though they are now odly cemented, and daubed together with untempered morter, cannot but wonder at your account of things palpably deſigned long ſince, and now ſo viſibly here acted, where their Enemies known intereſts, and their own preſent ſufferings are ſo conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and correſpondent, and anſwer as lively as faces in a glaſſe. We may ſuppoſe that ſome of our Enemies are dementated by God, but we may withall ſuppoſe that there is a moderate ſort, ſuch as the Arguilians amongſt the Scotch Presbyterians, and ſuch as the Hoptonians amongſt the Engliſh Prelaticall Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leers, that may finde their old ſuſpitions ſtrangely ſympathizing with theſe diſcoveries. It muſt needs be evident to the Arguili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by this time, that their young King, when he had ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Covenant, and was bound thereby to proſecute all Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall, Popiſh Cavaleers, yet at the ſame time intended that <hi>Montroſſe</hi> by his Commiſſion ſhould confound all Covenanters by Prelaticall, and Popiſh Cavaleers; but the particular paces, and gradations which He made, when he deſigned things ſo contrary, and the propoſed means of accompliſhing the ſame, will be now better underſtood then ever. Likewiſe by this time it muſt needs be evident to the Hoptonians, that the ſame young Maſter of theirs, when he went to Maſſe with his Mother in <hi>France,</hi> and Courted the Pope, and all Catholick Princes for aids againſt his Hereticall Rebels in <hi>England,</hi> He yet was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the ſame time to ingage himſelf by the Scotch Covenant to extirpate all Popery and Prelacy. But it will be now more evident to them, what the particular inductions, conjurations, and myſteries of the Romiſh Cabal was, which made that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation betwixt things ſo irreconcileable in his weak, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed underſtanding. Theſe myſteries after you are once through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read, and ſtudied, will appear no great myſteries: that which before was onely intelligible, by your Narrative of particulars will be preſented as viſible. He that has eyes to ſee, will not ſhut them at your ſcenes; he that has eyes, but not to ſee (for ſuch there were in our Saviours days) will be as ſtupified though a meſſenger from the dead came to ſalute him. In you are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the world ſtrange counſells, ſtrange actions, and ſtrange events, and the ſymetry that is betwixt your events and your actions, betwixt your actions and counſels, muſt needs convince
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:165723:26"/> every man, who is not cauteriſd by the unſearchable judgments of God. In ethicks wiſdom is juſtified by her Children, and Truth has the looking-glaſſe of time, and times events to view herſelf in, even as in the Mathematicks, <hi>Rectum est ſui Index, &amp; obliqui.</hi> I need ſay no more: ſeeing men will judge of this peece of yours by the times; and know the times by this peece of yours: for a Lamp brought into a dark roome makes it ſelf known, as well as all other things in that roome.</p>
                  <p>Give me leave to Print, and binde up together with this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of yours, two Letters which were communicated to me lately from a cordiall Friend, and I beleeve they will not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very heterogeneous. I will paraphraſe nothing upon them, let them paraphraſe for themſelves. <hi>Adiu.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> deſires to know my opinion touching his Majeſties Affairs, I ſhall with all freedom communicate what I conceive in ordinary reaſon, to be the moſt probable courſe for his re-advancement, and the reſtitution of <hi>Monarchy.</hi> And as touching this, the ſureſt way to proceed in is, to take a ſurvey of the cauſes of its ruin, and alſo of the Scotiſh Intereſt, ſince it pretends a reſtauration of the regall. Whence the deſtruction of the Engliſh <hi>Monarchy</hi> proceeded, may eaſily be perceived, if we conſider the time of its <hi>deelenſion,</hi> which began with the daies of our departure from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: For, during the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of that profeſſion among us, the <hi>Faith</hi> of the people being ſubjected to the Dictates and Decrees of the <hi>Church,</hi> they were like <hi>wax,</hi> apt to receive the Impreſſion of any <hi>Principle,</hi> which the <hi>Church</hi> was pleaſed to impoſe upon them; and ſo by reaſon of that compliance which was mainteined between the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Monarch,</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and the <hi>Lords,</hi> for their mutuall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, the people were the more eaſily ridden, and ſeldom or never contemn'd the <hi>Bridle.</hi> By this means, in thoſe dayes, <hi>implicit faith</hi> and <hi>blinde obedience</hi> was a <hi>maxim</hi> that paſſed current in <hi>Politicks,</hi> as well as <hi>Eccleſiaſticks,</hi> whileſt the <hi>great ones</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity</hi> ſhared all Authority between Them: And though many Quarrels aroſe between the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Monarch</hi> touching their ſeverall Juriſdiction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Arcana Imperii</hi> were
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165723:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtill kept under <hi>lock</hi> and <hi>key,</hi> and ſo their Authorities remained entire ever, in relation to the people. But when the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion began to take place among us, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſoon loſt the command of thoſe <hi>Reins</hi> which they held over the <hi>Conſcience; Implicit obedience</hi> was immediately caſhired, and the people ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving liberty allowed in things <hi>ſacred</hi> made bold to prie into the <hi>Civill,</hi> and the reverential law to the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> being quitted, the leſſe reverence was born to the <hi>regall Authority.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſſe, the <hi>reforming Clergie</hi> (to make amends) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured what lay in them to eſtabliſh their own <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and twiſt it again with that of the <hi>Crown</hi> upon a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Account; and as to outward ſplendor, they ſeemed to make the <hi>King</hi> ſomwhat more than he was before, plundring the <hi>Pope</hi> of the Title of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head of the Church to beſtow it upon him. And farther, it muſt be acknowledged, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> did what lay in them to ſupport and advance his Prerogative; and they did it a long time: But alas, the <hi>firſt Reformers</hi> having open'd the eyes of the People, their Succeſſors knew not which way, to ſhut them up again, becauſe the multitude were inſtructed in time to know as much as themſelves; and knowledg is ever attended with a deſire of liberty, and will require ſatisfaction in reaſon, before men will yeeld up their Intellects and obedience.</p>
                  <p>Hence it was, that after men had a liberty given to read the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> they made bold of Themſelves to interpret (every one after his own ſence) as well as to read, and by this means they furniſht themſelves with matter enough to pelt at the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> which order of men being beaten down as the main pillars, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſaw the neceſſity of a Fall of the Monarchy it ſelf. Upon this account came in the <hi>Presbyter</hi> with his new Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hewn out of the Scriptures to ſupplant the Proteſtant, and after him the <hi>Independant,</hi> who fetches Arguments likewiſe from the ſame Fountain, which puzzle all the world to prove the neceſſity of any Nati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nall Form of Church-government at all; and ſo the harmony betwixt the two <hi>Polities</hi> of Church and State being loſt, it is obvious to every common underſtanding, that a change of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, was the originall, or the firſt moving Cauſe, of this alteration of government, and the ruin of Monarchy in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Cauſe of the diſeaſe being known, I ſuppoſe it is no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:165723:27"/> hard matter to preſcribe his Majeſty a remedy for recovery: And to this end, his beſt courſe is, to take the Counſell of <hi>Hippocrates, Contraria contrariis curanda.</hi> Since the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings have loſt the Crown by departing from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, ſure the way to get it again is to return thither, and if it can be re-gained upon that Account, it will never be loſt again: For, if I have any judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Affairs of this world, certainly there is no way left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven to allay the preſent Opinions and ſubdiviſions of <hi>Faction</hi> in point of Religion, and to compoſe the civill <hi>Feuds</hi> that follow them, but by reducing the Members of this diſtracted Body, and ſwallowing up all, into a <hi>Monarchicall Catholick</hi> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. For, as things now ſtand, and as long as there is an Indulgence of that humor called <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible this Nation ſhould be in any Form but that of a <hi>Republick;</hi> and untill <hi>Conſcience</hi> be muzzled again with the old Catholick Bond of <hi>Implicit obedience,</hi> it will ever be barking, and except ſuch a Principle come in credit, it would be as impoſſible for his Majeſtie to keep poſſeſſion hereafter, as it is now to get it, upon any other Terms, than an engaging with and for the <hi>Catholick</hi> Religion.</p>
                  <p>And that there is no way but this for a recovery, will be made very evident by ſtating the condition of thoſe parties in the three Kingdoms that pretend to his <hi>reſtitution;</hi> which I ſhall now effect in brief. The party that makes moſt noiſe in this particular is the <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> and at preſent there is a ſtrong Report of his Majeſties Inclination to Them; but how ſuch a Courſe can be juſtified in reaſon, I do not ſee, ſince there is no poſſible <hi>medium</hi> to reconcile the two Polities, <hi>Regall</hi> and <hi>Presbyteriall,</hi> they being as contra-diſtinct in nature, as <hi>unitas</hi> and <hi>multitudo, Monarchy</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd <hi>Polyarchy,</hi> both claiming (not an equalitie of power, but) the <hi>Supremacie:</hi> And though the Presbyterian claims his, in a way collaterall (that is, <hi>In ordine ad Spiritualia)</hi> as to civill Things, yet the pretended derivation of their Authority more directly and immediately from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as his ſpeciall Miniſters, and ſole Adminiſtrators of his diſcipline (to whoſe <hi>Scepter</hi> all earthly powers ought to bow, and obey) cuts the very Throa of all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Power, and (by conſequence) aſſaſſinates the regall dignity. This being the true nature of that <hi>Faction,</hi> I ſuppoſe his Majeſtie hath little Cauſe to be in love with it, or to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leeve he can by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:165723:28"/> imbarquing himſelf in that bottom, make a ſaving voyage up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the preſent Adventure, ſo as to return like himſelf, or to be what he would be.</p>
                  <p>Nor do I ſee, what probability can be therein, to carry the day againſt the preſent prevailing party in <hi>England.</hi> That brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reed <hi>Scotland,</hi> is the grand <hi>Aſylum (In quo n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Boreas ipſe mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re velit;)</hi> and whether the poverty and puſillanimity of the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Rabble be able to ſtruggle with the wealth and power of <hi>England,</hi> is well worthy Conſideration. As for their Party among the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the chief Actors (the curtain being now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>drawn) are become inconſiderable and contemptible, and <hi>Presbytery</hi> it ſelf (in the latitude demanded) is univerſally odious to the Nation: Some Remnants they have likewiſe in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but not fit to be named, in order to the great work of reſtitution. Moreover, it is to be obſerved, that a Cloſe with that party, will utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblige thoſe two grand ones, the <hi>Royall-Proteſtant</hi> and the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now as touching theſe two, it is true indeed, they ſeem at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in a very low condition, but their hearts are firm, their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber great, and as long as they are ſo, nothing wants but means and opportunity which muſt be ſought after; and neither of Them being to be had at home, the Riſe of all muſt be from abroad. And if we look into forein parts, the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> hath but few <hi>Friends,</hi> the <hi>Catholick</hi> many. The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> can do much joyned with the <hi>Catholick,</hi> but nothing without him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the key of the work, muſt be to bring theſe two to an union; which I ſuppoſe is no hard matter to effect, ſince the late looſnes in Church diſcipline hath rendred the Proteſtant or Epiſcopall Cavaleers (as they call them) very indifferent, either to be of no Religion, or of any, as is evident by the many Proſelites which flow in daily unto the Church of Rome: Beſides it is a thing not diſputed now, but firmly beleeved by moſt of the ingenious and generous ſort of our Nobility, Gentry, and old Clergy, that the difference betwixt us and Rome is not in fundamentals, but only in a few ceremonies and circumſtantials, which though they formerly ſeemed ſuperſtitious extravagancies, yet now are lookt upon by them (as with an eye of experience) to be neceſſary points of Prudence, <hi>Infatuare plebem,</hi> to charm, and keep the world in order. Theſe things being conſidered, it will be no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165723:28"/> for his Majeſty to mint the old Proteſtant and Catholick with the ſame ſtamp, and make them both bear the ſame Royal Image and Superſcription. As for pretences of Conſcience, which may ariſe to oppoſe the reaſon of this, I ſuppoſe his Majeſty can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but have ſo much of <hi>Prince</hi> in him, as to know it is a meer va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to puzzle Conſcience in matters of Ceremony; and there is not a Chaplain of his, but muſt be maſter of ſo much reaſon as to give him full ſatisfaction touching this particular: But if his Clergies Doctrine will not do it, yet let him be convinced, and inſtructed by the example and practiſe of his heroick Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, the great <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> who judging the differences in Religion not to be fundamentall, made no ſcruple to take the Catholick way, when he could not come by the Proteſtant, to a plenary poſſeſſion. And my opinion is, if his Majeſty take the ſame Courſe, the Pope himſelf, and all the Catholicks through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Europe, prizing England highly, will uſe all means for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; which will be ſo much the more eaſie to attain upon that ſcore; in regard the Catholicks, or ſuch as are at leaſt half-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, are now chief in poſſeſſion of the kingdom of Ireland; who would all be extremely diſtaſted, and not ſo cordially per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the Royall Intereſt, if once his Majeſty ſhould make a reall cloſe with the Scotch Presbyterians.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſſe, though a reall Cloſe would be deſtructive, yet I cannot but recommend a pretended one, to be of all other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, the moſt neceſſary to carry on his Majeſties deſigne, that whileſt he ſhakes hands with them in publick, he ſtick faſt to his true Freinds in private. And above all things it were requiſite his pretences be kept ſo high ſtill toward the Presbyters, that they have no cauſe to ſuſpect him: For, if he effect nothing elſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, yet this great benefit muſt needs enſue, that it will obſtruct any union or Accord, and maintain Freinds, betwixt Them and the Independents. By any means let all arts be uſed to keep theſe from uniting, and then the work is half done to his hands, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it will be little leſſe then impoſſible. <hi>Liberavi animam meam.</hi> Let my Lord know I have delivered my opinion with all ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and freedome, being confident I ſhall ſtand upright in his Judgment and his Majeſties, when they have well weighed my Allegations. I am,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>(Sir)</salute>
                     <signed>Your very affectionate humble Servant: M. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:165723:29"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Received yours of the 8th. inſtant, and the ſame day I went and ſhewed his Lordſhip, who went immediately and impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to his Majeſty, who hath kept it lockt up ever ſince in his Cabinet. I perceive, that in the judgment of them all you have hit the nail on the head, and his Majeſty reſolves to ſend a copy of it to the Queen at Paris, to whom I know it will be every jot as welcome. You might imagine, that I flatter you, if I ſhould deliver the opinions of his Majeſties true Friends, in the ſame language that they expreſſe, concerning your extraordinarie parts and merits; but take this for all: They ſay, there never came a more judicious and ſolid expreſſe from any Engliſh pen; and it is exceedingly wondred, that you ſhould jump ſo evenly in your judgment with the greateſt heads in <hi>Europe,</hi> upon whoſe Counſell and Advice his Majeſty ſolely depends; And this ſo exactly (my Lord ſaith) as if you had converſed and compared notes together.</p>
                  <p>As for the Scots, aſſure your ſelf his Majeſty abhors them, any farther than for his own ends; and it hath been already reſolved to keep cloſe (touching them) to the Rule preſcribed in your letter; therefore be not moved at all, if you chance hereafter to hear of our agreement with Them: For, it is the Queens Advice, we ſhould do it upon any Terms whatſoever. For news, I refer you to the incloſed Copie, deſiring to hear from you upon all occaſions; but this peice of good news more give me leave here to tell you, that you will never want a gracious Maſter of his Majeſty, who expects your privacy, and is reſolved fully to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you, as ſoon as it ſhall pleaſe God to reſtore him: And touching this, you will ſuddenly receive greater Teſtimonies and Aſſurances than mine; in the mean time he ſhall take all opportunities to premove that good opinion which you have already attained, and uſe my utmoſt endeavour every way to deſerve the reputation of,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Qui Decipi vult, Decipiatur.</q>
               <q>
                  <l>Some fall, becauſe they will not ſtand:</l>
                  <l>Some ſhip-wreck, cauſe they will not land:</l>
                  <l>No pity: let him ſnared be:</l>
                  <l>That ſnares diſcover'd will not ſee.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
